<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aurora Ismenia and the prince: by Don Juan Perez de Montalvan. Oronta the Cyprian virgin: By Signr. Girolamo Preti. Translated by Thomas Stanley Esq;</title>
            <title>Aurora, &amp; the prince.</title>
            <author>Pérez de Montalván, Juan, 1602-1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90454</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1468</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1422_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202332</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862659</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862659</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114828</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90454)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114828)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 182:E1422[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aurora Ismenia and the prince: by Don Juan Perez de Montalvan. Oronta the Cyprian virgin: By Signr. Girolamo Preti. Translated by Thomas Stanley Esq;</title>
                  <title>Aurora, &amp; the prince.</title>
                  <author>Pérez de Montalván, Juan, 1602-1638.</author>
                  <author>Preti, Girolamo, 1582-1626. Oronta.</author>
                  <author>Stanley, Thomas, 1625-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, with additions.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[8], 87, [3], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Wilson for Humphrey Moseley at the sign of the Princes Armes in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first English edition (Wing P1467) title reads: Aurora, &amp; the prince.</note>
                  <note>Oronta has a separate divisional title page, and separate pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>"As the Oronta was included in the Poems 1651 (pp. 181-194), sheet H was omitted in those copies of the present which were issued appended to the larger collection"--Pforzheimer catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114828:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AURORA
<hi>ISMENIA</hi>
AND THE
PRINCE:
BY
<hi>Don Juan Perez de Montalvan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ORONTA
THE
Cyprian Virgin:
BY
<hi>Sign<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Girolamo Preti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tout vient a poinct qui peut attendre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated by <hi>Thomas Stanley</hi> Eſq;
The Second Edition, with Additions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Wilſon</hi> for
<hi>Humphrey Moſeley</hi> at the Sign of the Princes
Armes in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114828:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114828:2"/>
            <head>The Reader</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay be pleas'd to take Notice,
That what hee hath in his
hand, was undertaken with
no other Intention, then as
an exercize of both Languages; That
it now comes abroad in Obedience to
private command, which could not be
withſtood; That the Licentiouſneſſe
of the French Tranſlation brings hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
no aſſiſtance: But if he finde the
Names of Perſons or Places differ from
the Originall, let him ſuppoſe it done
for the better accommodation of the
Scaene.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomia">
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:114828:3"/>
                  <head>Upon A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RORA.</head>
                  <l>THis Tranſplantation of <hi>Sicylian</hi> Loves</l>
                  <l>To the more pleaſing ſhades <hi>Albions</hi> Groves</l>
                  <l>Though I admire, yet not the thing betrayes</l>
                  <l>My ſoule to ſo much wonder as the waies</l>
                  <l>And manner of effecting; that thy youth</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntravail'd there, ſhould with ſuch happy truth</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlock us this <hi>Iberian</hi> Cabinet,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Diamonds you in poliſht Engliſh ſet:</l>
                  <l>Such as may teach the eyes of any Dame</l>
                  <l>I'th' Britiſh Court to give and take a Flame.</l>
                  <l>But here the greateſt Miracle we ſee,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Spain</hi> for this hath travell'd unto thee.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>W. H.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:114828:3"/>
                  <l>LAnguage and Wit, which equally diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>Both light and life to Poetry and Proſe,</l>
                  <l>In this traduction as their Orbe doe ſhine,</l>
                  <l>And make theſe Stories, like thy ſelfe, Divine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurora</hi> brighter then ſhe was of late.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Prince</hi> in his misfortunes fortunate.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Montalvan</hi> proud to ſee himſelfe out-done,</l>
                  <l>By a Reflection clearer then his Sun.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>W. F.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:114828:4"/>
                  <l>TRanſlations that ſhould give light,</l>
                  <l>Eclipſe their Authors from our ſight;</l>
                  <l>But here like Chriſtalls doe convey</l>
                  <l>The luſtre of a forraigne day:</l>
                  <l>Which the inlightned world might ſee,</l>
                  <l>Is owing to thy Charity,</l>
                  <l>Who reinſpir'ſt <hi>Aurora's</hi> cheek</l>
                  <l>With ſuch freſh Roſes, that we ſeek</l>
                  <l>Truth in th'originall, which <hi>Spaine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To owne muſt borrow back againe.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. H.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:114828:4"/>
                  <head>Upon ORONTA.</head>
                  <l>FLames reſcu'd faire <hi>Oronta</hi> from the power</l>
                  <l>Of an inſulting <hi>Thracian</hi> Conquerour.</l>
                  <l>The Fame of which brave action <hi>Preti's</hi> Rhime,</l>
                  <l>Freed from the greater tyranny of Time:</l>
                  <l>Yet in that freedom ſhe leſſe glories, then</l>
                  <l>In being thus made Captive by thy Pen.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>E. S.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:114828:5"/>
                  <l>FArre brighter now in thy Poetick fire</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oronta</hi> ſeemes then in her fatall Pyre;</l>
                  <l>For there, her beauty loſt, her vertue ſhines;</l>
                  <l>But thy admir'd expreſſion both combines;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Cyprus,</hi> whoſe beſt glories here are ſeen,</l>
                  <l>Is prouder of her Virgin then her Queen.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>W. F.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114828:5"/>
            <head>Aurora.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ionyſius</hi> the Sicilian Tyrant had a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
for her Celeſtill beauty named <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rora,</hi>
not more faire then unfortunate; &amp;
ſcarſe had ſhe compleated the laſt yeares
of her Infancie, when Heaven was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to let her know that ſhe was beautifull by eclipſing
her fortune. For Nature, as if ſhe eſteem'd beauty a
crime, &amp; not her owne image, doth for the moſt part
puniſh it: The Mother of <hi>Aurora</hi> dyed; and <hi>Dionyſius,</hi>
although the loſſe of his wife gave him no reall reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
expreſt in feign'd teares how extremely he lov'd
her; but within a few days diſcover'd the hypocriſie of
his griefe, receiving in her place <hi>Arminda,</hi> an Italian
Lady of quality, but not worthy of that Crowne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
he had many yeares before kept her as a Miſtris.
She was of a lively ſpirit, witty and faire; but of a
diſpoſition ſo harſh, that ſhe gain'd little upon the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
of the people, bearing ſuch command over
her husbands actions, that ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> permitted not any thing
to paſs in the Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me, without firſt conſulting her
pleaſure; a care proper to ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h of ſmall worth, as
make oſtentation of the power they enjoy, that by
this meanes they may diſſemble their low beginnings;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114828:6"/>
but the ſuceſſe proves contrary, in regard the injur'd
by murmur and complaints diſcover more then was
imagin'd. <hi>Aurora,</hi> conſidering that to permit ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
were to lend wings to her pride, advis'd her not
to rely with ſo much confidence on her fathers affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
ſince it was not impoſſible that it might faile, &amp;
then would ſhe fall lower for not having treaſured the
good will of his ſubjects: adding moreover that ſhee
ſhould remember what ſhee was formerly, that ſhee
might not vainly be tranſported with her new eſtate.
Theſe words ſo incens'd <hi>Arminda,</hi> that from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward
ſhe plotted <hi>Aurora's</hi> death; and to effect her
deſire made <hi>Dionyſius</hi> beleeve that ſhee was jealous,
telling him hee lov'd his daughter ſo paſſionately,
for being the picture of the dead Originall; ſince
as the Phoenix leaves her aſhes to perpetuate her ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion,
ſo affection uſeth to leave ſome living pledges
to preſerve its memory: and certainely, the neglect he
ſometimes expreſt towards her, was occaſion'd by
that dead love pictur'd in the beauty of <hi>Aurora. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minda</hi>
urg'd this ſo earneſtly, that <hi>Dyoniſius</hi> making
impiety a Complement, reſign'd his daughters fault
into her hands, allowing her in this cauſe to be both
Judge &amp; Party. Love the common excuſe of all extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagace
did not here acquit <hi>Dioniſius;</hi> for a man is not
oblig'd to diſpiſe the pledges of his blood for a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
that diſſembles when ſhe weepes, and weepes
when ſhe pleaſes. <hi>Arminda</hi> was ſatisfied, ſo that <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rora</hi>
were in ſome remote place out of her ſight;
whereupon her Father commanded her to depart out
of <hi>Sicily,</hi> chuſing rather to live without a daughter,
then diſpleaſe a wife; ſuch was the affection of a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114828:6"/>
blinded Lover, the raſhneſſe of an unnaturall Father.
They conveig'd the faire Princeſſe to a little Iſland,
ſeated betwivt (the two Promontories) <hi>Pelorus</hi> and
<hi>Pachynum</hi> which ſeem'd as a Garland of Flowers in
the Tyrrhen Sea; it was done privately to avoid the
mutiny of the people, who lov'd her for her beauty
and her vertue: Hee order'd a ſelect number of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
for her attendants, with forfiture of life to
any who ſhould diſcover that <hi>Aurora</hi> reſided in that
narrow Pallace. The diſcreet Lady did with much
wiſedome beare her Fathers unkindneſſe, diverting
her minde now with the muſick of the little wanton
Birds, which hearing her name thought it ever mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
and ſung continually: Now with the pleaſant
wind which ſporting upon the ſmoothneſſe of the
Chriſtall ſea did amorouſly diſquiet it: now with
reflecting on her owne misfortunes, for the unhappy
are often recreated with the ſame thing that afflicts
them: Now with the Ladies that attended her, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
with <hi>Celia,</hi> who being of the ſame age and
kindred well deſerv'd her privacie; but when all
fail'd, and nothing could delight her, ſhe took an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument
which in her hands might boaſt it was not
dumbe; and weeping ſung thus:</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>When will arrive the Day,</l>
                  <l>Which muſt my life and ſorrowes terminate,</l>
                  <l>That angry fortune may</l>
                  <l>(The tyrant goddeſſe of all humane ſtate</l>
                  <l>Her crueltie fulfilling)</l>
                  <l>By one kinde death thus make an end of killing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114828:7"/>
                  <l>When ſhall my troubled yeares</l>
                  <l>Be to a verdant grave of flowers reſtor'd?</l>
                  <l>My injuries, my feares,</l>
                  <l>Too little merited, too much deplor'd?</l>
                  <l>When ſhall my juſt complaint</l>
                  <l>From equall heaven receive a full reſtraint?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now I am throwne thus low,</l>
                  <l>What more can be deſir'd by cruell Fate;</l>
                  <l>No hope my ſad thoughts know,</l>
                  <l>Of reinjoying their paſt happy ſtate:</l>
                  <l>Oh my afflicted minde!</l>
                  <l>Death would'ſt thou come, a welcome thou ſhalt finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With patience forlorne,</l>
                  <l>I paſse the Moneths, the yeares in ſolitude,</l>
                  <l>The Evening and the Morn:</l>
                  <l>In vaine my hopes thus ſtriving to delude,</l>
                  <l>My teares I conſtant keep,</l>
                  <l>And as I am <hi>Aurora,</hi> daily weep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When the Rebellious Sea,</l>
                  <l>Armed with Snow, ſtrives to ſubdue this Rock,</l>
                  <l>It ſeemes my miſerie,</l>
                  <l>At once kindly to warne, and rudely mock:</l>
                  <l>For ſo the Deſtinies</l>
                  <l>My life each minute offer to ſurprize.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114828:7"/>
                  <l>Soon as the morne appeares,</l>
                  <l>And uſhers in with dubious light the day,</l>
                  <l>My reall ſorrow weares</l>
                  <l>So true a ſhade of death, that I betray</l>
                  <l>My reaſon to that dreame,</l>
                  <l>And (though awake) dead to my ſelfe do ſeem,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All things within my view,</l>
                  <l>All things that grow and thrive by Natures care,</l>
                  <l>My ſorrowes doe renew:</l>
                  <l>For by ſucceſſive change they better'd are,</l>
                  <l>But to me fortune ſtill</l>
                  <l>Is therefore conſtant, 'cauſe ſhe firſt was ill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Tree from January</l>
                  <l>No livery but the hoarie Froſt receives,</l>
                  <l>Yet May its dreſſe doth vary,</l>
                  <l>Proudly adorning it with painted leaves:</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the fruitfull plaine,</l>
                  <l>What Auguſt ſtole, April reſtores againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Sea ſomtimes enrag'd,</l>
                  <l>Swells up in Chriſtall mountaines to the skies,</l>
                  <l>Yet often is aſwag'd:</l>
                  <l>But onely I in conſtant miſeries,</l>
                  <l>Confin'd to endleſſe griefe,</l>
                  <l>Expect no liberty, nor hope reliefe.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Aurora</hi> clos'd this ſweet Muſick with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Sighes and Teares, that hee muſt have had a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114828:8"/>
ſoule truely inſenſible, that could heare her without
Compaſſion. One evening as ſhee entertain'd her
ſelfe with the preſent proſpect of the ſea, ſhee ſaw
a man ſtrugling with the waters, and breaking the
waves, though hee relyed more on the mercy of a
Planke, then the ſtrength of his armes, endeavouring
to recollect his fainting Spirit, till he might approach
the ſhore for preſervation of his life. <hi>Aurora</hi> mov'd
with a noble pitty, and tender feare to have him die
before her eyes, commanded thoſe few that attended
her, to relieve him: who putting to ſea in a little
Skiffe, took him up and treated him moſt carefully;
(for ſo <hi>Aurora</hi> had commanded them) beſides the
perſon and civilty of <hi>Pauſanias</hi> (for that was his
name) mov'd them to reſpect and affection. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
recover'd from his rough uſage, (which had
caus'd him to vomit much water) he ſhar'd amongſt
them ſome Jewells, which hee had preſerv'd from
the ſea in his late danger; telling them that he was
nobly deſcended, and that untill he ſaw his fortune
amended, it was neceſſarie for him to live conceal'd;
and therefore deſir'd the company to accept of his
ſervice, for that poſſibly hereafter it might not repent
them of that favovr. His gold and perſon had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd
the affection of thoſe that heard him: they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd
thanks for the complement, promiſing to ſerve
him to the utmoſt of their power. <hi>Pauſanias</hi> was
glad, conceiving hee might ſecurely continue there,
without being known; for that Iſland was little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
with other, then the watchfull Guardians
of that beauty, which ſo unjuſtly ſuffer'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Going forth
one night when the bright <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with her beames
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114828:8"/>
enlightned the Wood, hee heard a voyce that with a
chearefull ſweetneſſe thus related its griefe to the
Birds and Waters:</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>From th'early Dawne untill the Sun retire,</l>
                  <l>I to theſe woods and hills my griefe exſpire;</l>
                  <l>My eyes with boundleſſe Rivers over-flow,</l>
                  <l>Like troubled Fountaines murmuring at my woe:</l>
                  <l>Perpetuall miſeries I ſtill deplore,</l>
                  <l>As they are mine: but as immortall more.</l>
                  <l>What is't by nature beauties wealth to owne,</l>
                  <l>If to theſe woods confin'd I live alone:</l>
                  <l>Or that my eyes have power to kill with love;</l>
                  <l>If neere me none but birds and beaſts doe move?</l>
                  <l>Too cruell heav'n that know'ſt my innocence,</l>
                  <l>Or with my ſorrowes, or my life diſpence.</l>
                  <l>Thou to torment me doſt forbid me die,</l>
                  <l>For death is pleaſing unto miſery:</l>
                  <l>Let thoſe that happy are enjoy their breath,</l>
                  <l>The wretched never live but in their death.</l>
                  <l>To each dull houre that ſlides through lazy day,</l>
                  <l>My griefes or memory of griefes I pay.</l>
                  <l>Thus live I, only pleas'd with this reliefe,</l>
                  <l>Death is the lateſt remedy of griefe.</l>
                  <l>For patience failes where th'injur'd ſoule ſuſtaines</l>
                  <l>The rigour of unintermitted paines.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanius</hi> was aſtoniſht as well at the ſweetneſſe
of the voice, as to heare it in ſo ſtrange a place, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring
who it could be, whoſe ſoul ſo feelingly deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
its owne misfortunes: and as well that he might
not be ungratefull for the favour he recived, (though
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114828:9"/>
he were ignorant from whom) as to try, if by this
meanes he might come to know the divine owner of
ſo ſweet a harmony, to the ſuſpence of the liſtning
Nightingales he ſung this ſong.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Torment of abſence and delay,</l>
                  <l>That thus afflicts my memory,</l>
                  <l>Why do'ſt thou kill me every day,</l>
                  <l>Yet will not give me leave to dye?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why doſt thou ſuffer me to live?</l>
                  <l>All hope of life in life denying?</l>
                  <l>Or to my patience tortures give,</l>
                  <l>Never to dye, yet ever dying?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To faire <hi>Narciſſa</hi>'s brighter eyes,</l>
                  <l>I was by loves inſtruction guided,</l>
                  <l>A happineſſe, I long did prize,</l>
                  <l>But now am from their light divided<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Favours and gifts my ſute obtain'd,</l>
                  <l>But envious Fate would now deſtroy them;</l>
                  <l>Which if to loſe I only gain'd,</l>
                  <l>What greater paine then to enjoy them?</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>The ſame wonder which before ſeiz'd <hi>Pauſanias,</hi>
ſurpriz'd <hi>Aurora,</hi> knowing none of her ſervants were
of ſuch extraordinary parts, or could ſo ſweetly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine
of the inſupportable torment of abſence. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rora</hi>
inquiſitive to know, and incited by the curioſity
that is incident to women, was deſirous to ſee the
<hi>Orpheus</hi> of thoſe Rocks: but the ſhadow of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114828:9"/>
trees, the diſtance of place, and above all, the
regard of her quality which detained her, repreſt
this deſire, ſo that ſhe deferr'd it till ſome other time;
and calling one of her attendants, demanded of him,
if there dwelt any in that wood, beſides thoſe that
came with her out of <hi>Sicily.</hi> The ſervant anſwered,
ſhe forgot him, whom not long ſince ſhe commanded
them to ſuccour, ſeeing him in danger of his life.
<hi>Aurora</hi> asked if he knew who he were? Hee replyed,
he knew no more then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t he had ſaid he was call'd
<hi>Pauſanias,</hi> concealing his quality and country, yet
could aſſure her, that he ſeem'd to be of noble Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
or at leaſt his perſon and ſpirit deſerv'd to bee
ſo. <hi>Aurora</hi> would not enquire further, leſt her curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity
might breed ſome ſuſpition; and although it be
true, that none can love what he never ſaw, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd
with; yet Fame, Vertue, and Deſert incite a
deſire to ſee whether that ſatisfie the eye, which had
by the eare affected the ſoule. Wee will not ſay
<hi>Aurora</hi> was in love, though her ſolitude might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
it, her greatneſſe would not conſent to it: Yet
ſhe had a deſire to know the man ſo well qualifi'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> ſoone ſeconded this deſire, for not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring
the myſtery incloſed in the Palace, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
to frequent the place where he firſt heard her:
and <hi>Aurora</hi> had the opportunity many evenings of
ſeeing him paſſe by with ſuch a grace as might endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
the liberty of one leſſe reſtrained then ſhe was:
for the afflictions of love are not for thoſe that have
other misfortunes to reſent. <hi>Pauſanias</hi> could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
the faire <hi>Aurora,</hi> the windowes and lattices de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar'd
him her ſight, neither would he diſcover himſelf
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114828:10"/>
to thoſe hee convers'd with; ſuppoſing, that ſince
they kept their buſineſſe ſo private, the ſecreſie much
concern'd them, and therefore he conceal'd what hee
deſir'd: For it is a rule of diſcretion to know no more
of any man then he is willing to communicate. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe,
deſiſted not to proſecute his intentions,
hoping he might finde opportunity to ſee that ſweet
Syren. The morning often found him under her win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,
not knowing whom he courted, loving in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;
yet confident more then a private Lady was
within thoſe Walls. Before the Pallace he us'd ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
paſtimes and recreations, that hee might thereby
obtaine a ſight of the Goddeſſe whoſe voice had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted
his ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> had good ſucceſſe in all things, having bin
brought up in the exerciſe of arms, he hunted the wild
Beaſts of that wood ſo fortunately, that he made their
deaths acknowledge him Maſter of their ſtrength and
furie. There was not any in the Pallace but applauded
his gallantrie; only <hi>Aurora</hi> was perplext at his perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions;
for every day he encreas'd her affection by new
deſerts. And although ſhe lik'd all ſhe ſaw in him, yet
the inequality ſhee conceiv'd was betwixt them diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd
her diſcretion, thoſe that diſparage themſelves
being unexcuſable. Hereupon ſhe adviſed, whether
it were not expedient to have him kill'd; for when a
meane perſon may occaſion extraordinary miſchiefe,
his death is eſteemed mercy: but ſhee could not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
it in earneſt: For, to take away the life of thoſe
we love, becauſe we love them, is no good reaſon in
the ſtate of affection; ſhee would have him depart
the Iſland, but immediately ſhe repented: For it is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114828:10"/>
hard to put that out of ſight which is imprinted in the
minde: In effect, ſeeing that to kill him were cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
to <hi>Pauſanias,</hi> to baniſh him tyranny to her ſelfe, ſhe
reſolv'd to divert her ſadneſſe, paſſing her ſolitary
houres with more delight; and that he might never
know that it was ſhe that lov'd him, ſhe exchanged
names with <hi>Celia,</hi> to whom ſhe imparted the Plot,
that ſhe might aſſiſt her in purſuit of it, and with her
name diſſembling her quality, ſhee reſolv'd to give
entertainment to this new affection, untill ſhe might
know who he was that had wone ſo much upon her
heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aurora</hi> might ſafely have admitted to her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
the affection of <hi>Pauſanias,</hi> for he was ſole heire,
to the King of <hi>Macedonia;</hi> and being enamoured of
the fame of <hi>Aurora's</hi> beauty, which verſes and
pencills had extoll'd, whilſt other Princes by Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors
ſolicited her marriage, reſolv'd that his fortune
ſhould rely upon his owne diligence, and by going to
<hi>Sicily</hi> to be both the Agent and the Lover: This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
made him put to ſea, and forſake his owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey;
ſuch is the power of a noble reſolution, ſo did
the imagined beauty diſquiet the Princes minde, and
attract his will and freedome, that he expos'd his life
to the perrill of the waves, and his greatneſſe to a
meane lodging of Planks and Canvas, to ſee if truth
were correſpondent to ſame. But he was leſſe fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
then adventrous; for one evening the Sea being
angry, or weary to ſuſtain the weight of ſo high a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
in ſo little room begun to rage furiouſly, ſo that
the valiant Princes life was in danger; the heavens
were darkned, and the Aire ſo turbulent, that the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114828:11"/>
company expected every minute, ſhould end their
lives, and without thought of ſaving themſelves
made him leap into the foaming Sea, fearing ſome
worſe event; and by embracing a plancke, to uſe the
moſt difficult meanes for his owne ſafety: Thus paſs'd
he two dayes befriended by the weather, at length ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived
ſo neare the Iſland, that <hi>Aurora</hi> could relieve,
and after love him ſo extremely as we ſee.</p>
            <p>She reſolved at laſt to ſpeake with him, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the feigned name of <hi>Celia,</hi> which defire was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed
by <hi>Pauſanias;</hi> for one night he amorouſly
ſung theſe Verſes upon the curioſity of his love.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>What wouldſt thou have unquiet breaſt?</l>
                  <l>What is it thus diſturbs thy reſt?</l>
                  <l>Say not thou lov'ſt, it cannot be,</l>
                  <l>Who never didſt deſerve or ſee.</l>
                  <l>Love, where the mind out-ſtrips the eye,</l>
                  <l>Is onely Curioſitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But thou wilt ſay, why doſt purſue</l>
                  <l>Thine owne diſquiet then? 'tis true;</l>
                  <l>And though this onely care expreſſe</l>
                  <l>Of an imagin'd happineſſe,</l>
                  <l>Deſire to ſee doth ever prove</l>
                  <l>A ſure preparative to love.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An object ſo divine I frame</l>
                  <l>Within my breaſt, as doth inflame</l>
                  <l>My captiv'd mind: I love, ſubdue,</l>
                  <l>Deſire, oblige, hope, and purſue,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114828:11"/>
                  <l>Reſigne my liberty, beſtow</l>
                  <l>My ſoule on one I do not know.</l>
                  <l>And thus can Maſter be of none,</l>
                  <l>For I no longer am mine owne.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>As ſoone as <hi>Pauſanias</hi> had made an end, <hi>Aurora</hi>
call'd to him and ſaid, (though with ſome difficulty,
by reaſon that the Balcon's were very high) that he
might leave his curioſity, and profeſſe love: For his
addreſſes were not unacceptable. <hi>Pauſanias</hi> remain'd
contented with this favour, ſince although hee had
never ſeene the beſtower, yet at leaſt his affections
were not ſo ill plac'd as he before imagin'd; and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
it vvas not poſſible to ſpeak to her, he determin'd
to vvrite, transferring his thoughts to the Penne,
vvhich uſeth to bee the diſcreeteſt tongue, expreſſing
more then is felt. The Letter vvas ſhort (though
the ſubject did not require it) to leave her vvith the
deſire of receiving another: and thus it ſaid:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> May juſtly ſay you are obliged to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor
me, having coſt mee infinite cares,
without any recompence, although ever
ſince the laſt night I have preſum'd to
be more fortunate, and ſo am reſolv'd to
dye rather importunate then baſhfull: for
my birth is noble, and will not ſuffer mee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114828:12"/>
to flie from any attempt. That which I
now deſire, is to ſee you, if perhaps my
love have merited it; and ſince heaven
ſuffers it ſelfe to bee lov'd, and you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
ſuch, bee like it in condition as in
beautie: for if your beames inflame mee,
it is but juſtice I ſhould know the ſphere
from whence they come.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> repaired thither as hee uſed to doe, and
having firſt courted her with a Song, which hee had
compoſed that day, as well ſung as penn'd, he ſhew'd
her the Paper, ſaying it was a piece excellent for
Muſick, and that he ſhould be extreame glad to heare
it ſet to the Gittrah. <hi>Aurora</hi> underſtood him, and
was pleas'd with the deceit, becauſe that which
otherwiſe would have appear'd lightneſſe, now paſt
for civility, (for there are ſome ſo diſcreet in what
they demand that by encouraging the crime, they
ſeem to excuſe the fault) and throwing downe a
ſtring of Pearle, <hi>Pauſanias</hi> return'd it more weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
then before: <hi>Aurora</hi> read the Paper, and in part to
ſatisfie his expreſſions, deſiring him to expect a while,
commanded <hi>Celia</hi> to write, not that ſhee could not
her ſelf, (for ſhe was extreamely accompliſh'd in every
thing) but for the danger might enſue, if her hand
were knowne; and betwixt them both they fram'd
this Anſwer:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:114828:12"/>
THat you may not when you returne
home to your Countrey accuſe the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilian</hi>
Ladies of ingratitude; ſince your
deſire is ſo reaſonable, as the ſight of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
I will performe what you require me;
though then your eyes will contradict your
fancie; for it is certaine, that I am fairer in
your opinion now, then I ſhall bee after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward:
I am call'd <hi>Celia,</hi> and attend a
Lady of quality that lives in this Caſtle:
She and I will be to morrow in this place,
ſo that you may then ſee me; bee of good
courage, and thanke me for being ſo ſoone
quit of your love, if that can be love, which
hath paſt no further then imagination: I
only entreate you to keepe this indiſcretion
ſecret, and to tell me your name, eſtate, and
quality, for it imports us both.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> kiſt the Paper, and read it often: for a
Lover is never ſatisfied at the firſt, &amp; the day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
went to ſee what hee ſo much deſir'd. <hi>Aurora</hi>
had commanded her ſervants to retire to another
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114828:13"/>
quarter of the houſe, and being alone with <hi>Celia,</hi>
cauſed her to attire her ſelfe richly, and ſhee ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide
her. <hi>Pauſanias</hi> beholding, was exceedingly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſht,
in regard his fancy had come ſhort of the truth;
for <hi>Celia,</hi> beſides her ſlender ſhape, was of a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
beauty; but her luſtre was eclips'd by <hi>Aurora's</hi>
preſence, whoſe eyes were ſpheres of light, her fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head
a plaine of Lillies, her haire the riches of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia;</hi>
in her cheeke Roſes, her mouth Pearles, her neck
of Alabaſter, her breaſts of Snow, and hands of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht
Ivorie; ſhe was attir'd in greene Tabey, wrought
with gold, ſo that ſhe appear'd like a Diamond encha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
in Emralds, her Gowne Skie-colour, laid with
black Buttons and Loopes: in a word, ſhe was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
divine, her perfections many, and her yeares few.
<hi>Pauſanias</hi> was much aſtoniſhed, yet fearefull the Sea
ſhould ſee her, leſt he ſhould wooe her for one of his
waterie Deities; and thanking his own perſeverance,
hee determined to gaine her that had got his ſoule,
though at the expence of a long abſence from his
Countrey: for he found that the Picture of <hi>Aurora</hi>
that he had ſeen was farre un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quall to the divine <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia:</hi>
he eſteemed the time well employ'd that he had
ſpent in adoring thoſe Walls, ſince within them hee
had found ſo much more then expectation had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.</p>
            <p>Whilſt <hi>Pauſanias</hi> enjoy'd theſe favours paſſing the
night with them, and the day with hopes, it happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
that <hi>Dionyſius</hi> ſent for one of thoſe that waited on
<hi>Aurora,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d threatned him, that if either through
his or his fellows fault, it ſhould be known where his
daughter was, they ſhould inſtantly dye a ſhamefull
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114828:13"/>
death. With this feare he returned to the reſt, and
gave them notice how much it concerned them that
<hi>Pauſanias</hi> would quit the Iſland, ſince he might eaſily
at one time or other, as he walked in the wood, ſee
the Princeſſe, and occaſion all their ruines: So eaſie is
it, replyed another, that I thinke he pretends, if he
have not already effected it: for I have obſerv'd, that
he looks up very intentively to thoſe Balcones; and
ſhe hath enquired of me who he is; and if he perſiſt,
hee muſt of neceſſity come to know her, and we to
loſe <hi>Dionyſius</hi> favour. In effect, feare overcame them,
and all agreeing that hee ſhould not continue there,
they advertis'd him that it concern'd his life to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> wondred at their ſuddaine reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and after many conjectures began to ſuſpect that
without doubt ſome one of them lov'd <hi>Celia,</hi> and
would uſe that meanes to ſecure his jealouſie or envy:
and thereupon he determin'd to ſpeake to them all,
that he might ſatisfie him who conceiv'd himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd,
and to beſeech them againe not to offer him ſo
great a diſcourteſie, as to conſtraine him to depart the
Iſland, untill ſuch time as he had news of his ſervants,
whoſe lives perhaps the Sea had pardoned. He plainly
perceiv'd how difficult it was to reclaime them, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
thoſe that before ſo kindely entertain'd him,
now behold him diſtaſtefully (for ill will is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd
by the eyes, countenance, and carriage) and
one morning finding them altogether, hee ſaid to
them:</p>
            <q>
               <p>Gentlemen and friends, my birth is noble, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114828:14"/>
though I live where I am unknowne to all but my
ſelfe, I doe not thinke any here can complaine of
my demeanour, for men of my parentage receive
not benefits unthankfully, (ingratitude and noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
differing as night and day) I came to this
Iſland, or to ſay better, my fortune threw me here,
not unhappily, ſince in it I have found both protecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on,
and friends. Here I have liv'd a while, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring
to ſatisfie to my power, though not to my
deſire, the favours I have receiv'd from all: but it
ſeemes I have not ſufficiently expreſt my ſelfe; ſince
when I think you moſt my friends, you threaten me
with death unleſſe I depart: I have enquired what
might be the reaſon, but indeed can finde none, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
ſome one of you being jealous, incites the reſt
to this violence: which if it be ſo, hee ought to
conſider, that a man doth not offend, unleſſe hee
know that he injures; for he who through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
or innocence ſollicits that whereunto another
hath right, can onely then be ſaid to offend, when
after he knowes the truth he purſues his wiſh; and
ſo to have ſurveigh'd this Caſtle, with a deſire to ſee
what it inclos'd, or by curioſity to have obtein'd
that fight can not diſquiet any one; for before this
preſent I knew not that it would give offence;
and if I conceive aright, there is more then one
Goddeſſe inhabits there; ſo that none hath reaſon
to complaine of mee, becauſe I neither injur'd
him out of malice, nor can he know to which I am
enclin'd.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> thought by this to have appeas'd and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114828:14"/>
ſatisfied them, but the event was contrary, for the
knowledge of this ſecret being their greateſt feare,
they needed no other information to draw their
ſwords, and aſſault his life. But before they could
diſpatch it, <hi>Aurora</hi> and her gentlewomen hearing the
noiſe, ſaw the treacherous miſchiefe they intended to
a ſingle ſtranger, and forgetting her greatneſſe, (for
love conſiders not quality, when that which is eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
is in danger) ſent to command them all to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt,
and informe her of their quarrell; who comming
before her, related what charge her Father had given
them, adding, that <hi>Pauſanias</hi> for certaine either
had already, or elſe meant to ſpeak with one of the
Ladies that attended her highneſſe; which might
give occaſion to diſcover what <hi>Dionyſius</hi> intended
to keep ſo ſecret, that none but heaven and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
ſhould know, and therefore to excuſe the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
that threatned them, it was neceſſary to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
his life.</p>
            <q>
               <p>It would be (replyed <hi>Aurora</hi>) impiety in me
to conſent to it, and treachery in you to effect it,
becauſe I am informed you have received courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies
from this Gentleman, &amp; there is no reaſon you
ſhould take away his life, whom you your ſelves
confeſſe to be of ſuch eſtimable parts; eſpecially
for that which may be remedied without bloud. I
underſtand that <hi>Pauſanias</hi> ſaw one night one of my
women, whom either for the novelty, or opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
he courted, and ſhe (I think) heard him not
unwillingly; For this reaſon it concernes me that
he ſtay no longer in this Iſland; and ſince his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
is ſufficient to ſecure you, I take that and your
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114828:15"/>
danger upon my ſelfe, for <hi>Pauſanias</hi> is a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
and can conceale what he hath ſeen.</p>
            </q>
            <p>With theſe hopes they were ſatisfied, and <hi>Auro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi>
remained in a thouſand perplexityes: for ſhe lov'd
him ſo paſſionately, that there would be but little
difference betwixt looſing him and her owne life.
And indeed ſo powerfull was his diſcourſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,
that although he had been leſſe worthy of
her beauty, yet to ſee and heare him would beget affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:
And at laſt ſhe became ſo reſolute, that it
would have grieved her to have been freed from her
priſon, if ſhe ſhould thereby be deprived of his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
converſation: for women, when they once fall
in love, are ſenſible neither of paines or misfortunes
which befall them in the company they affect:
wherefore ſhe conſidered by what meanes ſhe might
comply with her own affection, and her ſervants
feare. To keep him there againſt all their wills were
to hazard her honour, and to give her enemies an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
of a more ſevere revenge. Having firſt adviz'd
with <hi>Celia,</hi> ſhe writ a Letter, wherein ſhe inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
him of what had paſt, entreating him affectionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to preſerve his life, and to prepare for departure;
two things in appearance contrary. When night
was come, the faire Princeſſe went forth to take
leave of <hi>Pauſanias,</hi> and delivering him the Letter,
with a little Silver Cabinet wrapt in Taffata, not
having power to ſpeake, ſhee withdrew her ſelfe, to
lament her enſuing misfortunes. <hi>Pauſanias</hi> alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd,
through the ſuſpition of the late quarrell, and
kiſsing the Signature, which ſaid, <hi>Your Celia,</hi> he
read it with much feare, on this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:114828:15"/>
SIr, I have had much care for you this
day; I ſaw you draw your Sword, and
I aſſure you it troubled me: I think it was
love, yet unfortunate, ſince it muſt dye
as ſoone as borne. We are both the cauſe
of it, becauſe I gheſſe our affection hath
been diſcovered. My birth is more noble
then you imagine; and it concernes us both
that you immediately abſent your ſelf, that
you loſe not your life, nor I my reputation.
(Believe mee I am very ſenſible of it,
for in a word, I love you, and muſt loſe
you. You may comfort your ſelfe with this
thought, that it was impoſſible I ſhould
ever have been yours, not for love to any
other, but for my qualitie too tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.
I ſend you here a thouſand Crowns
to ſerve you in your journey, with a knot
of Diamonds and Emeralds, which I
did ſometimes weare at my breast, that in
your Countrey you may remember it was
mine, and its owner yours.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:114828:16"/>
Having read and deplor'd the rigorous ſentence
of his death, hee reſolved preciſely to obey all that
<hi>Aurora</hi> in it had commanded, and to let her know
ſome part of his regret, he tooke the Pen, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd
this anſwer:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Should have eſteem'd it a happineſſe if
to day I had received death by my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
(ſince ſuch they were) that I might
not have expected it from your hands: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the mornings light breakes forth, I
will abſent my ſelfe from yours, that you
may ſay I knew how to love and to obey
you: What I would not doe for my owne
life, I will for your honour: I cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
what I feele, becauſe I write perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and can aſcertaine nothing; onely I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
you my bloud is ſo noble, that the King
of <hi>Syracuſe</hi> himſelfe cannot ſay hee is my
better. I came out of my Countrey to
marry in this Kingdome, &amp; for your ſake
will return back. I give you infinite thanks
for your Preſent, and will not excuſe my
ſelfe from repaying it hereafter. The knot
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114828:16"/>
I will keepe as your favour; and ſince you
have given me ſo much cauſe of griefe, give
me time to lament it, though I hope ſo to
reſent it, that when you leaſt thinke of it,
you will heare newes of his death, who
knew how to love you, but had not the
happineſſe to deſerve you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aurora</hi> with much trembling made an end of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
the Letter, and not able to reſtraine her eyes,
bath'd it in teares. <hi>Celia</hi> came to her, and tooke out
of her hand the occaſion of her griefe, but that little
avail'd, for ſhe tooke it not out of her breaſt; ſo that
as ſhe went through a long Gallerie, ſhe wrung her
hands, beſeeching heaven to increaſe her Fathers ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour,
and <hi>Arminda's</hi> hate, that they might contrive
her death. She went to looke towards the Sea, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining
that her loſt lover was already embarqued;
and comming thither, ſo exceſſive were her teares and
paſſionat expreſſions, that <hi>Celia</hi> fearing ſhe might of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
ſome violence to her ſelfe, amongſt other reaſons
ſaid thus to her.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Is it poſſible Madam that a diſproportion'd affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
ſhould ſo extremely work upon you! I ſhould
not have beleev'd this of your reſerv'd diſcretion,
if I had not ſeene it. I confeſſe <hi>Pauſanias</hi> deſerves
to be lov'd, but you know he is not a man equall to
your condition, nor can in reaſon be yours; what
proofe have you of his diſcent, more then his owne
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114828:17"/>
relation? which may well be doubted, for the
meaner ſort where they are not knowne, give large
teſtimonies of their bloud. Alas (replyed <hi>Aurora</hi>)
that uncertainty is my greateſt trouble: If <hi>Pauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi>
be as noble as he hath intimated, perhaps I
might have attempted ſomething you would little
have ſuſpected from my reſervedneſſe; and I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
my ſelfe it might yet well be done, were it
but to free my ſelfe from impriſonment: And
though I ſhould marry into a ſtranger Country, I
ſhould not loſe my right to the Kingdom after my
Father; I believe his Subjects affect me ſo entirely,
that if they knew I were here in priſon, he would
have little ſecurity either of his Kingdome or life.
Tell me <hi>Celia,</hi> what can I hope for in this Caſtle
but death? My Father is married, and in love: <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minda</hi>
governes the Kingdome, and beares mee ſo
much ill will, that I many times eat my meat in
feare, ſuſpecting ſhee hath ſent ſomething to kill
me, though I ſhall now need no other poiſon then
the abſence of <hi>Pauſanias.</hi> Oh <hi>Celia,</hi> you would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige
me, if you could contrive how I might ſpeake
with him, and be better inform'd of his quality, that
I may not continue thus in ſuſpence: If hee bee of
meane Parentage, I will rather dye by mine owne
hand, then admit a thought may ſtaine my bloud;
and if to my happy fortune he ſhould prove (as is
not impoſſible) ſome Prince caſt upon this Iſland
by accident, be confident, I would hazard my life
for my liberty, though in all things I ſhould firſt
take your advice, that I might not erre through
mine own opinion.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:114828:17"/>
               <hi>Celila</hi> was attentive to what ſhe ſaid, and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionating
her teares, began to conſider, if by any
meanes ſhee might come to the ſight of <hi>Pauſanias,</hi>
without endangering his life; ſhee had an acute and
ready wit, but withall accompanied with ſo much
diſcretion, that whatſoever ſhee undertook ſucceeded
happily. After much deliberation ſhee concluded,
that it was requiſite (for feare of his enemies) not
to ſee him for that time; but that he ſhould continue
ſome dayes in the thickets of that mountaine, and
then might come hither by night having notice gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
him by <hi>Libanius,</hi> (one in whom ſhe repoſed
truſt.)</p>
            <q>
               <p>Thus farre, replyed <hi>Aurora,</hi> you have well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
it, but what meanes remaines to ſpeake with
him? for to diſcourſe from hence is very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.
If you will not heare me make an end, (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
the diſcret <hi>Celia</hi>) neither can I let you know
the deſire I have to ſerve you, nor you your ſelfe
obtaine your affection: I ſay, Madam, that <hi>Pauſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi>
comming to theſe Walls may get up, by our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance,
&amp; the help of a Ladder, to this part of the
houſe adjoyning to your lodgings: ſo that I having
the key of the outward doore, you need not feare,
and by the Balcones that look towards the Sea,
may diſcourſe with him till you are ſatisfi'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
his birth. Conſider now, if you finde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
your ſelf love enough to embolden you for this
contrivement: for my owne part I aſſure you that
I am ready to loſe my life in your ſervice.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Aurora</hi> was by this much comforted, and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<hi>Celia</hi> a thouſand times; who by Letter advertis'd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114828:18"/>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> of her determination, ſhe charged <hi>Libani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>
to deliver him the Letter, and attend him as a
guide. <hi>Pauſanias</hi> had taken the road towards <hi>Sicily,</hi>
to try if hee might finde in that way any of his loſt
ſervants. <hi>Libanius</hi> over-tooke him, and deliver'd the
Letter and Meſſage from <hi>Celia: Pauſanias</hi> receiv'd it
as one that ſaw his dead hopes revived, and having
read it, &amp; rewarded the welcome newes, <hi>Libanius</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
him of what hee was to doe. So paſſing
through the wide wood, they came to a poore Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards
Cottage where <hi>Pauſanius</hi> ſtai'd, and <hi>Libanius</hi>
return'd to give his Lady notice of what had paſſed.
Hee continued there foure dayes, favour'd and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd
by <hi>Aurora,</hi> who every day ſent <hi>Libanus</hi> to
viſit him: and one night, as darke as the wiſh of any
Lover could paint it, he came to the Pallace, (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to the ſphere of the Sun of that Iſland) and
diſmiſſed <hi>Libanius,</hi> (for a ſervant may not bee wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
to every thing) then upon a ſigne given, <hi>Celia</hi>
and <hi>Aurora</hi> came forth, and letting downe a Ladder
of Cords, <hi>Pauſanias</hi> in a moment got into the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cone,
and having kiſt <hi>Aurora's</hi> hands as his Miſtris,
and <hi>Celia's</hi> as his Miſtreſſe's Lady, they led him
through many roomes, ſo richly furniſht with hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
chaires of State, and pictures, that it ſhewed no
leſſe magnificence then what he had forſaken in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia.</hi>
And comming to a part that excelled the reſt,
as being furniſh'd for ſtrangers, <hi>Aurora</hi> told him,
that he might abide there, intimating how requiſite
care and obedience were, and that to attempt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
was to put his life in apparent danger. Then
ſo farre replyed <hi>Pauſanias,</hi> I ſhall preſerve it ſafe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114828:18"/>
having no will but your pleaſure. <hi>Aurora</hi> gave him
thanks, telling him, that becauſe her Lady was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
ſhe omitted many things which ſhe reſerv'd for
more privacie; and taking her leave ſhew'd him the
Balcone by which they might diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> was well contented with his courteous
entertainment, paſſing the greateſt part of the day in
contemplating that miracle of beauty; their mutuall
affection increaſed equally (for by converſation love
out-growes his infancy) and as one night they were
both in diſpute, whether lov'd more truly (a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell
wherein it grieves none to be overcome) <hi>Aurora</hi>
with ſome expreſſions of reſentment, ſaid thus:</p>
            <q>
               <p>I have long deſired my <hi>Pauſanias,</hi> to know a
truth, though, for feare of expoſing my ſelfe to
the hazard of dying, I have not demanded it; but
that I may not remaine ever in this ſuſpence, I will
boldly adventure my life: It concernes me no leſſe
then my honour and quiet to know who you are,
that I may diſpoſe of my ſelf with ſome reſolution,
and hereof I require no other teſtimony, then to
know it from your own mouth: for I have ſo great
an opinion of you, and repoſe ſo much confidence
in your worth, that I am ſure you will not deceive
me. My birth is noble, and ſo noble that no woman
can boaſt higher bloud: for this Lady on whom I
wait (though my Miſtris) in this hath no advantage
of me, as, by the favour ſhe ſheweth me, you may
have gather'd the inequality is not much. The
reaſon why we dwell in this Caſtle, I will not
now let you know; though, if your anſwer ſuit with
my minde, you may: But in the meane time I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114828:19"/>
you by My ſelfe, by the love you beare me,
and by that you owe me, to ſatisfie me in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,
which I aſſure you detaines my ſoule in extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
affliction.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> obliged by <hi>Aurora's</hi> entreaties was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
to have diſcovered himſelfe; but that hee might
with leſſe difficulty be believed, he anſwered, that he
was onely Son to the Admirall of <hi>Macedonias</hi> a man
ſo eminent and beloved of the people, and of <hi>Time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nides</hi>
his King, that he poſſeſt the firſt place in his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
and in the government of that Monarchy. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rora</hi>
remain'd not diſcontented, ſince the innequalitie,
was not ſo great as might deface the pleaſing hopes
ſhe had imprinted in her breaſt. Onely <hi>Pauſanias</hi> was
angrie at himſelfe, being conſcious that to deceive
her who relyed ſo confidently on him was a kinde of
treachery: yet this offence was not inexcuſable, in
regard it is ſcarce eſteemed a fault to make uſe of a
ſlight deceit to compaſſe our deſire. He ſucceeded ſo
happily in his love, and ſo favour'd by the divine
eyes of <hi>Aurora,</hi> that though he were not naturally
diſtruſtfull, yet was he fully perſwaded of her affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
and not without reaſon, ſince the expreſſions he
had from her of this truth confirmed him in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aurora</hi> communicated to <hi>Celia</hi> all that had paſt;
reſolving at laſt to let <hi>Pauſanias</hi> know the true cauſes
of her impriſonment, that he might deliver her out
of it, and conveigh her where ſhee might be ſecure
from her unkinde fathers ſeverity; Yet would ſhee
concea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e this happineſſe a while, to make triall of his
conſtancy, whereof ſhe had no need to exact ſo many
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114828:19"/>
proofes; for he liued ſo contented onely in loving
her, that hee ſcarcely employed any other deſire,
though ſometimes he wiſht himſelfe elſe-where, that
he might enjoy a nearer converſation, yet with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
to her honour. As he continued in this mind, it
fortuned that <hi>Aurora,</hi> through ſome indiſpoſitions
could not be ſeene for foure dayes: <hi>Pauſanias</hi> bearing
with much impatience this abſence (along one to ſo
true a lover) reſolved to ſee her; and though ſuch
boldneſſe might violate the promiſe he had made,
he ſuppoſed the occaſion would excuſe him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
one night, forcing the lock, he came with as
much feare as ſilence to the bed where <hi>Aurora</hi> lay,
who had then yeelded to a ſhort ſlumber. He was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſh'd,
not without cauſe, to behold the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
piece of Natures Pencill; and ſetting down the
light he carried upon a little ſilver Cup-board, began
to contemplate that dead beauty, and living patterne
of Divinity. Her haire was looſe upon her ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
without more confinement then a green Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band;
her right hand under her cheek, and her left
careleſly upon the bed, which with a lovers timerouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
he took and kiſt. <hi>Aurora</hi> perceiv'd that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
did diſquiet her, with her eyes halfe open, like
the Sun when he wakens the day, ſaw a man at her
bed ſide; and as ſoon as ſhe knew it was <hi>Pauſanias,</hi>
warm'd with a modeſt baſhfulneſſe, ſhe chang'd the
Lillies of her Cheeks to Roſes: She asked him angri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
why he came thither; He anſwered to ſee her:
<q>I never thought (replyed <hi>Aurora</hi>) you had valued
me ſo low as to preferre your own pleaſure before
my entreaties, &amp; your curioſity before my honour.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114828:20"/>
I warnd you, that to ſtir forth, concern'd the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
and life of us both; which ſince you have
done, judge what I may juſtly thinke of you. You
will ſay Love was the cauſe: Preſumption deceives
you; you know ſuch teſtimonies better conſiſt with
the hazard of the man then of the woman. Reſerve
this freeneſſe, or rather boldneſſe, for women of
meaner quality: rudeneſſe is not pardonable with
every one: and be aſſur'd, I am herewith ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
that you cannot oblige me in all your life ſo
much as you have with this one action diſpleas'd
me. Returne to your lodging, and deſpaire not of
liberty, if you eſteem it an impriſonment to be thus
lockt up; to morrow I will ſpeak to my Lady, that
with her leave you may returne from whence you
came; ſo raſh a man is unfit for high deſignes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> would gladly have replyed to excuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
but <hi>Aurora</hi> would not ſuffer him, telling him of
the danger ſhe incurr'd, if he were diſcovered. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
thus forced to retire, hee wiſh't with griefe hee
might expiate this enterprize with the loſſe of life.
<hi>Aurora</hi> was not ſo much diſpleas'd as ſhe ſeem'd: Yet
to let him know the reſpect due to her perſon, and to
refine his affection, ſhe thought it diſcretion not to
ſee him for a few dayes.</p>
            <p>Meane while, the people (in <hi>Sicily</hi>) impatient
of <hi>Aurora's</hi> abſence (whom they extremely lov'd)
began to murmur at her Fathers cruelty, ſaying: what
mercy can Subjects expect from him that tyrannizes
over his owne bloud? It proceeded ſo farre, that
ſome with clamours, others with Armes, required the
reſtitution of the Princeſſe: The peoples inſolency
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114828:20"/>
affrighted <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> ſo that to diſmiſſe them, and to
comply with the deſires of his Subjects, Friends, and
Kindred, hee promiſed they ſhould all ſuddenly ſee
her: Hereupon he went out privately that night
with <hi>Clearchus</hi> his Favourite, and arriving where
<hi>Aurora</hi> was, excuſed his unkindneſſe, and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
the reaſon of his comming; hee comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
that immediately ſhe and her company ſhould
make ready, for they muſt with all ſpeed goe to
<hi>Sicily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aurora</hi> was ſo diſmai'd as might have given oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
of ſuſpition: <hi>Celia</hi> was ſtruck dumbe, and ſo
ſuddaine was their departure, that <hi>Aurora</hi> had not
time to weep. Nevertheleſſe, <hi>Celia</hi> ordered it
ſo that ſhee ſpoke with <hi>Pauſanias,</hi> but with ſo
much perplexity and feare, that ſhee was hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
underſtood, in interrupted expreſſions ſhee ſaid
thus:</p>
            <q>
               <p>Now, Sir, the time is come, that you may goe
out of this priſon, and enjoy the deſire you have
to ſee <hi>Sicily;</hi> there is a neceſſity that divides us. I
believe the love I bear you will ſeek you out where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
you are: One to whom my fortune hath
ſubjected mee (more ſevere then his relation
requires) enjoyneth me to live abſent from what
I moſt eſteeme; the occaſion is urgent, and he that
commands powerfull; ſo pardon me, and believe
it lies not in my power to excuſe it: a ſervant ſhall
come hither, to bring you ſafe into <hi>Sicily,</hi> though
not ſo ſoone as I could wiſh: more witneſſes
then ordinary ſee me. Heavens give you life to my
deſire.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:114828:21"/>
Sad and amaz'd was <hi>Pauſanias</hi> at this accident;
Sad, becauſe <hi>Celia's</hi> words ſeemed to imply that he
muſt loſe her; and amaz'd, as being ignorant of the
cauſe: hee could not apprehend the meaning of what
hee had heard; ſometimes imagining that hee was
ſentenc'd to depart in puniſhment of his late bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;
ſometimes that ſhe meant to abſent her ſelfe;
and that which held him in greateſt ſuſpenſe, was
the reflecting on her words, That <hi>one to whom by
fortune ſhe was ſubject, leſse mercifull then his rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
required, commanded her not to ſee him.</hi> A
thing which ſhe had ever conceal'd from him; but
ſhee referred the diſcovery of this truth to time, the
undeceiving Glaſſe. The day following paſt, and
neither <hi>Celia</hi> nor the maid appointed to attend him
viſiting him; the night came, when making his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed
ſignall from the Balcone, he was anſwer'd
by his owne eccho: then liftning at the doores,
and perceiving that all things were in deepe ſilence
hee ſuſpected one of theſe two things, either ſome
ſtrange accident had happened, or <hi>Celia</hi> dwelt no
longer in that place; having ſurpaſt thoſe doubts;
he reſolved not to ſuffer himſelfe to languiſh, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
opening the firſt doore with a Dagger, hee went
ſo farre till he came to the Chamber of his abſent
Miſtris, where looking round about, and finding
nothing but a diſmall ſolitude, hee began to thinke
all was illuſion and witchcraft; and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently
expected his death: Yet being Maſter of no
leſſe valour then diſcretion, he drew his Sword, and
went up and down the Caſtle to try if hee could
free himſelfe out of thoſe enchantments: at length
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114828:21"/>
comming into a Hall, which to his thinking was the
laſt, he ſaw a ſmall light, and a little further foure
men: Drawing neare them he ſaid, they muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſuffer him to goe out quietly, or prepaire for
Death; for hee was ſo reſolute, that their lives
ſeem'd but few to his indignation. They, amaiz'd
to ſee a man where the Sunne (the great Lynx of
Heaven) could hardly enter, to doe their office,
drew their timorous ſwords upon him: But hee had
endangered all their lives, if one of them, laying
hold of a Halbert, had not held it to his breaſt. The
valiant youth was mov'd; for feare his excuſable
where the multitude of enemies may aſſault on every
ſide; Yet conſidering withall, that to render him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
were to runne the hazard of being carried diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourably
to <hi>Sicily,</hi> he would rather undergoe the
danger, then preſerve his life with the ſtain of Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard;
He charg'd them to diſpatch him, or elſe hee
would adventure to change fortunes with them. At
theſe words they were all daunted, and through feare
had not courage enough to ſtrike. At laſt they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed,
not onely to let him depart, but that one
ſhould accompany him paſt danger of the way; becauſe
that place was ſo encompaſt with Mountaines and
woods, that they who were beſt acquainted with the
Deſart, often loſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> gave them thanks for the curteſie,
though it rather proceeded from feare then good
will; and taking leave of them, went forth into
the wood, with one that held himſelfe the moſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant
among them: Before they parted, hee entreated
him to tell him who was owner of that Caſtle; and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114828:22"/>
to oblige him the more, put into his hand a rich Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond
Ring; ſcarce had he receiv'd it, (though with
many proteſtations that hee needed not any reward
to ſerve him) when he confeſſed that it was a houſe
of Pleaſure, where <hi>Dionyſius</hi> us'd to divirt his minde
from the cares which attend affaires of State; though
it were long ſince he had reſorted thither, by reaſon
his faire daughter <hi>Aurora</hi> had dwelt there privately,
whom laſt night (mov'd by the importunity of his
Subjects) he carried back to Court. <q>Had this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
(ſaid <hi>Pauſanias</hi>) no Ladies that attended her?
Yes, replyed the timorus Flatterer, but there is
onely one, called <hi>Celia,</hi> who deſerves her affection:
For, beſides that her beauty is as ſingular as her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion,
ſhe is daughter to the Prince of <hi>Arſinda,</hi>
one of the greateſt and moſt eminent in all <hi>Sicily.</hi>
               </q>
               <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſanias</hi> with this information was leſſe afflicted:
Hee diſmiſs'd the Man, determining to goe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd
to Court, to ſee his deare, though abſent,
<hi>Celia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us leave <hi>Pauſanias</hi> in this Mountaine, whilſt
<hi>Aurora</hi> ſeeks meanes to advertiſe him of the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainneſſe
of her departure, and <hi>Celia</hi> writing (as
ſhe us'd) a Letter in her name, gave it to <hi>Libanius,</hi>
commanding him to go where he was, and to bring
him thence unperceiv'd if't were poſſible: It ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
not as <hi>Aurora</hi> and <hi>Celia</hi> deſir'd: For <hi>Clearchus</hi>
a Favourite of the Kings, had long lov'd <hi>Celia,</hi> and
ſhe favour'd him not onely by her eyes and affection,
but by the Pen, aſſuring him by many Letters, that
none but hee ſhould ever poſſeſſe her beauty. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
was ſhee miſtaken, in her choice: for <hi>Clearchus</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:114828:22"/>
in every reſpect was her equall, and had ſo high a
place in the Kings eſteeme, that he was never from
his ſide. This love was kept ſo private, that none
but her ſelfe and Heaven knew of it. <hi>Clearchus</hi> by
chance asking <hi>Libanus</hi> whither he went, he freely
told him, On a Meſſage from <hi>Celia.</hi> Seeing a Letter
in his hand he began to miſtruſt her conſtancy: for
long abſence occaſions ſuſpition of injury. Diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
himſelfe the beſt he could, he tooke Horſe and
went after him; but could not gueſſe at the end of
his journey, becauſe he went directly towards the Sea.
It was already night when he entred into a Fiſher-Boat;
<hi>Clearchus</hi> quitting his Horſe, went over with
him: when both were in the Wood, <hi>Clearchus</hi> bad
him deliver what he had about him; <hi>Libanius</hi> ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
he was a Thiefe, drew forth the Crownes that
<hi>Celia</hi> had given him, and laid them at his feet; then
begun to ſtrip himſelfe, to ſhew that he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
elſe about him. <hi>Clearchus</hi> finding the Letter,
promiſed him his life, if he would tell for whom
it was; and ſo wrought with him, that poore <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus</hi>
confeſſed all that he knew. <hi>Clearchus</hi> confirm'd
in his ſuſpition, reſtor'd him his Crownes, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled;
kept the Paper, and charg'd him to returne to
<hi>Cicily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clearchus</hi> remain'd ſolitary, grieving that he
thought himſelfe undeceiv'd; and finding a poore
Shepheards Cottage hard by, haſted thither, where
taking a fire-brand in ſtead of a Torch, he drew
out the paper, broke the Seale, and read what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:114828:23"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Have been very ſenſible of this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence;
the rather becauſe I am in ſuch
a condition, that I cannot communicate
my reſentment to you: My excuſe is
the truth, which you ſhall hereafter know
more at large. If upon ſight hereof you
come to Court and diſcover your ſelfe to
his Majesty, I am confident his Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
will eſteeme of you according to
your merit. That you may the leſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay
the performance of this requeſt, I
ſay no more, but that I am (as ever)
Yours,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>CELIA.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Nothing can expreſſe the paſſionate furie, or the
Arguments wherewith this miſapprehending Lover
complain'd of <hi>Celia's</hi> ill uſage, and the injuſtice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
his affection. Hee was about to goe backe,
with intent to teare him in pieces who was the cauſe
of this jealouſie; but a compaſſionate Shepheard
diſſwaded him, entreating him to paſſe the reſt of the
night under that Shed: for to doe otherwiſe would
ſhew indiſcretion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:114828:23"/>
               <hi>Clearchus</hi> (though with ſmall content) yielded,
and laying himſelfe down upon a freſh bed made of
Flags and Hay, ſaw hard by him a man ſleeping,
who by his ſhape and perſon ſeem'd of the beſt
quality: demanding who he was, the Shepheard
anſwer'd, that foure houres ſince he came to their
Cottage, and deſired to reſt under that Covert, to
avoid the ſharpeneſſe of the night. <hi>Pauſanias</hi> (for
it was he that ſlept ſo ſecurely, having his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
enemy beſide him, and had been glad to find
this poore Cottage where he might repoſe himſelfe,
wearied with Travell) awaking, perceived that he
was not alone, but heard him that was by him,
with ſad complaints curſe his Love, Jealouſie, and
Fortune.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> liſtning was troubled at what was ſaid,
but much more at the mention of <hi>Celia,</hi> a name
that diſquieted his ſoule. Obſerving him more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently,
he heard him thus diſcourſe to himſelfe:</p>
            <q>
               <p>Is it poſſible (ungratefull Woman) thou canſt
find in thy heart to diſpoſſeſſe an affection of ſo
many yeares and paines? Could not thy quality
acquit thee of lightneſſe? Oh <hi>Celia,</hi> how doth
a deceitfull promiſe misbecome one that profeſſeth
ſo much worth? Doſt thou ſo injuriouſly requite
ſo obſervant a Lover? I perſwade my ſelfe the
reaſon why thou enjoyneſt me to conceale my affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
was for feare of making thy <hi>Pauſanias</hi> jealous.
But I vow never to returne home, till he hath
ſatisfied my jealouſie: Ungratefull, I will begin
my revenge in killing him whom thou loveſt beſt;
I will proclaime thy lightneſſe: The World ſhall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114828:24"/>
know, theſe ſixe yeares that I have ſerved thee, I
have been in ſuch favour with thee, that thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
uſedſt Pen but to aſſure me thou wert mine.
Thou haſt deceiv'd thy ſelfe, falſe woman, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
me for a ſtranger, that cozens thee with
profeſſion of Nobility. What canſt thou ſay to
excuſe they ſelfe, ſince this Letter under thine
own hand ſpeaks thy unworthineſſe, and my miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> hearing this, was in ſuch perplexity
that he could not beleeve himſelfe to be awake.
Impatient that any man ſhould profeſſe himſelfe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor'd
of <hi>Celia</hi> (to defend her reputation, and to
chaſtize his fooliſh arrogance) he aroſe and told
him, that the part of his ſorrowes which he had
heard troubled him as much as himſelfe; but if a
ſight of <hi>Pauſanius</hi> would allay his anger, the laſt
night he was with a Gentleman of the ſame name,
and perhaps they might find him in the next Wood.
<q>I ſhall not be ſo happy, ſaid <hi>Clearchus,</hi> for I know
my ill fortune when I deſire a thing. Yes, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
you may replyed <hi>Pauſanias.</hi>
               </q> Then lighting a
dry Olive branch he invited him to come after, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minng
that within a few houres he would bring him
to him.</p>
            <p>Thus went they forth together, and coming to
the moſt intricate place of the Wood, <hi>Pauſanias</hi> ſtuck
the light upon a Tree, and drawing his ſword, reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely
ſaid to him:</p>
            <q>
               <p>I am <hi>Pauſanias,</hi> thy greateſt enemy; I love <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi>
and muſt enjoy her, though the King of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racuſe</hi>
himſelfe ſhould oppoſe it. Since thou ſaiſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114828:24"/>
that thou ſeek'ſt mee earneſtly, make uſe of this ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine
occaſion which is offer'd thee. If thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeſt
to draw thy ſword becauſe thou know'ſt mee
not, be aſſur'd, my quality is ſo noble, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
thinks he hath any advantage of mee, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives
himſelfe. I have ſerved <hi>Celia,</hi> if not with
as much ſecreſie, yet with more affection: if ſhee
heretofore lov'd thee, and now forgets thee,
complaine of thy fortune, not her eaſineſſe; and
ſince thou ſay'ſt the Letter which thou unjuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'ſt
was ſent to me, give it me, for I will put it a-amongſt
others that I have of hers; if not, Ile force
it from thee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <q>Doe not think (anſwer'd <hi>Clearchus</hi>) thy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces
move me: my heart is form'd for higher en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes,
and e're long thou wilt repent this
fooliſh raſhneſſe. Yet that thou maiſt know the
cauſe why I ſought thee ſo earneſtly, and with
what reaſon I complaine of <hi>Celia,</hi> heare her
falſhood, and thou wilt confeſſe that I have not
ſpoken very extravigantly of her. <hi>Celia</hi> and my
ſelfe have theſe many yeares reciprocally exchang'd
a pure and ſecret affection; but ſhee being neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated
to abſent her ſelfe from me for ſome reaſons,
I was ſo unhappy that in that time ſhee ſaw and
lov'd thee: if ſhe had neglected me for love of thee,
I had leſſe reaſon to complaine; but ſhee was
ſo farre from neglect, that ſhee never favour'd mee
with larger expreſſions then now; and that thou
maiſt not thinke theſe calumnies, proceeding rather
from jealouſie then the truth of one that reſpects
his honour, ſee whether it bee fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe or no:</q> ſo
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114828:25"/>
drawing out of his breaſt many Letters and Papers,
he caſt them at his feet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> read ſome of them; amongſt others his
owne, and another which the ſame day ſhe had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
to <hi>Clearchus.</hi> A good while he tooke not his eye
off from the Papers, it ſeeming to him impoſſible
there ſhould be in the world a woman ſo facile and ſo
cunning: but at laſt being fully perſwaded of her
falſehood, he gathered together all the cozening Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
and threw them into the fire, as if hee could
conſume ſo many deceits at once. Thereupon
<hi>Clearchus</hi> with his ſword in hand bad him, if hee
were a Gentleman, prepaire to defend himſelfe: for
it was not fitting it ſhould bee ſaid in <hi>Sicily,</hi> that
having had his enemy in the field he left him alive.
Thou ſhalt not need to prevent me, anſwered <hi>Pauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias,</hi>
for that was the onely reaſon why I drew thee
out into this wood: and ſo aſſaulting him furiouſly,
the Combate began, without any apparent advantage
on either ſide. <hi>Clearchus</hi> was the more weary, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
leſſe dextrous in the exerciſe of Armes. <hi>Pauſanias</hi>
avoiding a blow that he made, falſifi'd another, and
wounded him dangerouſly in the head. <hi>Clearchus</hi>
having his face bathed in bloud, loſt not his courage,
but enflam'd with revenge, aſſaulted <hi>Pauſanias</hi> ſo
deſperately, that he was forced to uſe all his skill to
guard himſelfe. The claſhing of their ſwords di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd
the Shepheards that went whiſtling their
Sheep together. They came in the inſtant, when
the loſſe of bloud abated ſtrength, but not courage in
<hi>Clearchus.</hi> They all ran in to him, ſeeing him the
more neceſſitated, and carried him home to their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114828:25"/>
Cottage, where with medicinall Herbes they enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd
and cured him.</p>
            <p>The valiant Prince (no leſſe aſtoniſh'd at the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
of <hi>Clearchus,</hi> then at the lightneſſe of <hi>Celia</hi>)
expected the approach of day, with intent to take
ſhipping, and returne to his Country. He went to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the Sea, and diſcourſing with himſelfe on
the various events of his fortune, ſaw a ſhip, which
by its loſſe of tackling and ſailes, ſhew'd it had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd
the anger of inconſtant <hi>Neptune.</hi> He obſerv'd
the Armes it carryed, and knowing they were his,
drew neerer to ſatisfie himſelfe: but this doubt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
not long; for <hi>Leontius,</hi> Sonne to the Admirall
of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> leaping a ſhore with his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
knew him, and gave thankes to Heaven for
the favour it had vouchſaf'd them in preſerving his
life.</p>
            <p>They related to him, how that after a long tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt
and imminent death, it pleas'd Fortune to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe
the Sea: But all of them bewailing their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
abſence, reſolv'd not to returne to <hi>Macedonia</hi>
without him, ſince hee might poſſibly eſcape alive.
<hi>Pauſanias</hi> gratified their noble reſolution with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
and rewards. Hee cauſed them to repaire
their Ship, determining to goe privately into <hi>Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi>
that they might not returne unſatisfied to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia;</hi>
to ſee if the Beauty of <hi>Aurora</hi> pleas'd
him; and to revenge himſelfe on the inconſtant
<hi>Celia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With this reſolution hee went to Court; but his
arrivall could not be ſo private, but <hi>Dionyſius</hi> had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
of it, and immediately gave him a viſit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114828:26"/>
ſuch extraordinary favours upon him, that
words ſufficed not to expreſſe his thankfulneſſe.
<hi>Dioniſius</hi> carried him to ſee the Princeſſe; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
her beauty to bee the chiefe motive of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
thither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> amaz'd when he perceiv'd <hi>Celia,</hi> to
whom he ſpake, to be by all call'd <hi>Aurora,</hi> was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
to have accus'd <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of impoſture; but <hi>Leon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi>
(who had beene Ambaſſadour before in <hi>Syra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe</hi>)
aſſuring him it was <hi>Aurora,</hi> hee was almoſt
diſtracted; and not treating with <hi>Dionyſius</hi> any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in that buſineſſe, he reſolv'd to returne to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia,</hi>
ſince a woman engaged to another in love,
was not fit to be his wife.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aurora's</hi> thoughts were very different from his,
for perceiving her good fortune, that <hi>Pauſanias</hi> was
every way equall to her, ſhee thought the time long
till ſhee had ſome meanes to accompliſh her affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Celia</hi> already was inform'd of the quarrell that
had beene betwixt <hi>Clearchus</hi> and the Prince. And
as <hi>Aurora</hi> was once complaining of him, for not
comming to ſollicite that which he ſo much deſir'd,
<hi>Celia</hi> told her, that the reaſon why hee was ſo
coole in his Love, was the deceit of her Letters,
and thereupon recounted all that paſt, advertiſing
her, that this miſtake was as well cauſe of her
loſing <hi>Clearchus,</hi> for hee was infected with the
ſame jealouſie; ſo that it concern'd them both to
diſcover the private deviſe her Love had made uſe
of. <hi>Aurora</hi> excuſing the Princes indifferency, in
regard it proceeded rather from his owne honour
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114828:26"/>
then neglect of her, called <hi>Clearchus,</hi> and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd
to him the whole buſineſſe, that he might
not ſuſpect any thing in prejudice of <hi>Celia's</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;
ſhe commanded him to go viſit <hi>Pauſanias</hi> from
her, and to let him know the miſtake that had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
him in jealouſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clearchus</hi> now freed from all former ſuſpition,
obey'd, and having kiſs'd the Princes hand, ask'd
pardon for drawing his ſword againſt him, though
unknown. <hi>Pauſanias</hi> told him, <q>he was engag'd
to love his valour, and to deſire his friendſhip. I
muſt requite this honour, anſwered <hi>Clearchus,</hi> with
welcome news;</q> and then related the occaſion of
<hi>Aurorah's</hi> living in the Caſtle; and how imagining
he was below her greatneſſe, ſhe had diſſembled
her name, changing it for <hi>Celia,</hi> untill ſhe were
fully inform'd of his condition; how to avoid the
danger of having her Letters known, ſhe cauſed <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi>
to write for her; how the reaſon of his going
to find him in the Wood, was becauſe he had for
many yeares loved <hi>Celia,</hi> as he had gather'd by his
words, and ſeeing the Letter with her Seale he was
confirmed in his jealouſie, blaming the affection of
guiltleſſe <hi>Celia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prince was ſurprized with wonder and joy
at this relation of <hi>Clearchus,</hi> and caſting his Armes
about his neck, in ſigne of love and delight, ſaid, the
news was ſo conformable to his wiſhes, that only
time could expreſſe how highly he eſteemed it. Then
went he to treat with <hi>Dionyſius</hi> concerning his love;
who promiſed her to him, thereby requiting the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement
of having left his Countrey; neither was
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114828:27"/>
any more worthy of the Princeſſe, and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
they writ to <hi>Timenides</hi> the Princes Father about
their agreement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> had now opportunity to viſit her, and to
expoſtulate the favourable deceit, whereby ſhe had
cauſed his jealouſie. Their Eſpouſals were ſolemnized
with the greateſt Pompe that <hi>Cicily</hi> ever beheld, joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
celebrating thoſe of <hi>Clearchus</hi> and <hi>Celia,</hi> whoſe
conſtancy merited a ſucceſſe no leſſe fortunate. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
a few daies they imbarqued for <hi>Macedonia,</hi> attended
by all the magnificence of the Court.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Timenides</hi> received them with the joy of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
who ſuppoſing his Son loſt or dead, found
him ſo much improv'd in all things; Then feeling
himſelfe burden'd with yeares, and through infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
unable to be the <hi>Atlas</hi> of that weight, he tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
the Crown to his Sons head: And that the
pleaſure of ſo true an affection might be compleat,
Heaven was pleaſed to beſtow on their firſt yeare a
Son. <hi>Pauſanias</hi> and <hi>Aurora</hi> living and loving ſo
unanimouſly that every day ſeemed the firſt of their
marriage.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:114828:27"/>
            <head>The Prince.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom the top of <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> a Mountain in
<hi>Armenia,</hi> deſcended a man, ſavage in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance,
though not in mind; cloath'd
with ſeverall skins of wild Beaſts, his
limbs ſtrong and ſwarthy, his face
ſcorch'd with the Sun, his haire long; at his ſhoulder
hung a Quiver of Arrowes, at his left ſide a Wood-knife,
and in his hand he carried a young tree, which
(being ſtript of the boughes and leaves) was both
his ſtay and defence; who ſitting down upon a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet
of ſweet though ordinary Flowers, drew out of
his breaſt a beautifull Picture, ſo lively in the obſcure
Tablet, that it ſeem'd to have more ſoule then it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
from the Pencill; and beholding it as inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively
as if it had beene the Originall; much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
he thus paſſionately diſcourſed to it:</p>
            <q>
               <p>Oh deare, though abſent <hi>Polixena!</hi> it is long ſince
I enjoy'd thy divine ſight in another condition:
but what aſsurance will not envy and fortune diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve,
where both conſpire to proſecute? When
I firſt caus'd <hi>Tebrandes</hi> to draw thy Picture in this
Tablet, I little thought that this unequall ſhadow
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114828:28"/>
of thy beauty ſhould ever have been my greateſt
comfort. Who would have ſaid when in <hi>Albania</hi>
I maintain'd a Tourney in a habit which thy faire
hands had embroydered, that I ſhould ever have
ſeen my ſelfe in an eſtate ſo different, the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
of a mountaine, my armes naked, my feet
covered only with the skin of a Beare, a Trunke
of a tree my Sword, my lodging a Cave, and
companions a pair of Lions? But the heavens know
that neither to be ſo expos'd to the injury of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
that the Sun takes me for July, and the
Snow for January; nor to be brought ſo low,
that I am forc'd every day to kill ſome wild Beaſt
to ſuſtaine me; nor to live in this diſmall ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude,
where I converſe only with Flowers and
Rivers; nor yet to conſider the ſmall hopes I have
of better fortune, have power to make me ſad;
but only the feare that thou doſt forget me: For
amongſt the troubles which an abſent Lover ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers,
none but this is able to torment him. It is now
twelve yeares ſince for thy ſake I firſt deſerted <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania,</hi>
and were my ſelfe dilated to an age ſhould
alwaies thus preſerve thee in my breaſt: but alas
I feare thou doſt not requite me: for women are
ſaid to place their eyes and wils only on what they
ſee preſent; becauſe what is paſt is no longer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd.
Having ſo long diſappeared can I doubt my
death is not believ'd for certaine? And ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
there are that affirme it, to comply with thoſe
that hate me. Yet if I live in thy memory, nothing
elſe can afflict or trouble me. I often imagine, that
as being but a woman, thou haſt prov'd unconſtant,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114828:28"/>
and though thy love might continue the firſt yeare
my abſence, yet ſure the ſecond thou tookſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
and the third didſt quite turne me out of thy
breaſt. However, this world hath had ſome, whoſe
conſtancy hath triumphed over the naturall imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celity
of their Sex; and thou maiſt bee one of
thoſe. The dagger of <hi>Lucretia,</hi> the Coales of
<hi>Portia</hi> and the Aſpes of <hi>Cleopatra</hi> teſtifie, that
Love is an unapprehenſive of Death. Thy conſtancy
(faire <hi>Polixena</hi>) would have had no ſuch incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience;
it would not have hazarded thy life.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The tender-ſavage Lover would have proceeded
in Diſcourſe to the Picture, had he not been inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
by a young Shepheardeſſe, who paſſing by
the skirts of a green Mountaine (imagining ſhee
was heard of none but the Birds) as ſhe went along
ſung thus:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Menga,</hi> a Shepheardeſſe, neare theſe Brooks borne,</l>
               <l>(Wonder o'th' earth, and envy of the morne,)</l>
               <l>Sad and aſham'd complaines of her hard fate;</l>
               <l>For beauty ſeldome proves more fortunate.</l>
               <l>Love whoſe ſoft chaines ſhe freely did diſpence</l>
               <l>To all, at leaſt enſnar'd her innocence.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anton,</hi> a Swaine, that many other eyes</l>
               <l>Attracted, was to hers a ſacrifice;</l>
               <l>Nor ſlights ſhe his affection, though ſhe feare</l>
               <l>Their envy who for him like paſſions beare.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tereſa's</hi> love ſhe knowes to him enclin'd,</l>
               <l>A Nymph though faire, yet wanton as the wind:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:114828:29"/>
Favours and gifts ſhe never yet withſtood,</l>
               <l>Inconſtancy deriving with her bloud:</l>
               <l>All that ſhee ſees her boundleſſe thoughts deſire,</l>
               <l>For longing fancies greedy eyes require:</l>
               <l>Once <hi>Menga</hi> found her with <hi>Anton</hi> leſſe coy</l>
               <l>Then ſhe could wiſh, his but to rob her joy.</l>
               <l>Shame did ſuppreſſe her anger, but her teares</l>
               <l>Did unreſtrain'd betray her jealous feares.</l>
               <l>What have I done, falſe ſhepheardeſſe ſhe ſaid,</l>
               <l>That thou ſhould'ſt all my happineſſe invade?</l>
               <l>Thou lov'ſt another, me haſt diſpoſſeſt,</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſtolne pleaſures are to thee the beſt:</l>
               <l>I've ſeen thee many love, but true to none,</l>
               <l>Thou doſt hereditary lightneſſe owne:</l>
               <l>Enjoy thine owne, not my delights remove,</l>
               <l>Thou wrong'ſt thy beauty to moleſt my love.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Menga,</hi> who againſt <hi>Tereſa</hi> cries,</l>
               <l>When ſhe begun to love, left to be wiſe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Geſimenes</hi> (for ſo was this prodigie of fortune
nam'd) was much aſtoniſht to heare ſo ſweet a voice
in a wilde wood unfrequented by any. He aroſe and
called to her, bidding her not feare, for he was a man
rationall as others, though his habit expreſſed no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
his condition. The timorous ſhepheardeſſe, when ſhe
ſaw his ſavage appearance, giving her ſelfe for loſt,
fled from this counterfeit Satyr, till ſtaid by weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
ſhee fell at his feet, ſo affrighted and out of
breath, that it pittied him he had overtaken her. When
hee beheld her divine beauty, hee thanked Heaven
that it had contracted its greateſt perfections in a
poore Shepherdeſſe. Neither did this admiration pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:114828:29"/>
from a forgetfulneſſe of his faire <hi>Polixena;</hi> but
the reaſon which induc'd him to this liking, was her
reſemblance of the other; ſuch as would confound a
Painter in drawing them both: He took her in his
armes and carried her to his poore Cave; where, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
firſt recovered her ſenſes with water, which
hee fetch'd in a Tortoiſe ſhell from the neighbouring
Rock, hee ſet before her Cakes and dryed fruits;
hee aſſured her that ſhee was not in danger; that his
quality was more gentle then his appearance pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd;
that ſhe might continne there in ſafety; and,
that her beauty had kindled in his breaſt ſo juſt an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
that though he had been ſavage indeed, hee
ſhould not have been ſo to her: for at the firſt ſight of
her an inclination did ſecretly invade his ſoul, which
oblig'd him not onely to honour, but to engage his
life for her. Therefore he entreated her by the great
reſpect which, in ſo ſhort a time, ſhe had gain'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
him, not to leave his company, but rather to help
him to paſſe the tediouſneſſe of that ſolitude, then
afflict his love by her abſence, which hee ſhould infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely
reſent.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Truely, replyed <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> (ſo was the Shepher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe
nam'd) what you require is not onely juſt, but
due to that civility and protection you promis'd;
beſides, it concernes my owne intereſt as well as
yours: for I am fled hither to avoid a man, to whom
my parents would have married me; one, they ſay,
doth every way equall me; but, to ſay truth, though
I was borne among the; Rocks, and am of a low
parentage, yet have I a ſpirit and thoughts ſo high,
that I am not in my owne opinion inferiour either
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:114828:30"/>
the heire of <hi>Albania,</hi> or the King of <hi>Armenia.</hi>
This morning I roſe with intent to ſubdue that ſelf-conceit,
and love him in obedience to thoſe that
perſwaded me; but finding I could not affect him,
nor reclaime my ſtubborne will, I ſtole away and
hid my ſelfe in this Mountaine, chuſing rather to be
a prey to the wild beaſts, then to one I could not
without diſdaine behold: though many women
are of opinion that converſation may produce affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;
yet could not I expoſe my ſelfe to ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
hazard, fearing the worſt: For the danger is
great which ſhe incurs, who out of this confidence
undervaluing her owne liberty, marries one that
ſhe abhorres. But becauſe I finde within my ſelfe
(beſides the thanks I owe your curteſie and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment)
ſomething that moves mee to love and
reſpect you; for though you appear outwardly a ſon
of theſe Rocks, yet your civill demeanour contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts
that appearance; I conjure you therefore by
your ſelfe to tell me who you are, and the reaſon of
your living in this Deſart; ſince we have agreed to
dwell together, and I have given you an account of
my fortune, it is fit you requite mee with the
like.</q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>This requeſt (ſaid <hi>Geſimenes</hi>) will much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict
me: the remembrance of miſeries cannot
bee renewed without teares, though I uſe often
to repeate mine to the heavens, to the fields, and to
this little river; yet becauſe in them you are my on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
comfort, and to ſatisfie in ſome manner for the
favour you do me in dwelling (as you have promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed)
with me, I will relate my birth, condition,
and misfortunes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:114828:30"/>
I am naturall ſon to <hi>Pharnazes,</hi> King of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania,</hi>
who dearely lov'd <hi>Clorinda,</hi> a Lady whoſe
eminence and merit made her hope to bee his wife,
&amp; in that confidence reſigne her ſelf into his arms;
but not long after was by reaſon of ſtate induc'd to
marry <hi>Rodantha,</hi> who prov'd with childe at the
ſame time that <hi>Clorinda</hi> my mother went with me:
I would to heaven I had never ſeen the light, (for
he that is borne to be unfortunat,e begins not his
life, but death.) So it happened that <hi>Pharnazes</hi> had
in one day two ſonnes, one by his wife, the other
by his Miſtris: and (though brothers) of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
fortune and quality, for <hi>Lucanders</hi> Mother
was the more noble: but who would think that
<hi>Pharnazes</hi> loving my Mother ſo affectionately, nay
ſhe her ſelfe, forgetting the paines, and griefe I had
coſt her, ſhould hate me: It was ſure the malignant
influence of my Starres which arriv'd at that hight,
that I was conſtrain'd when I would obtaine any
thing of my Father, to have recourſe to the Queen,
who though ſhe had a juſt reaſon to hate me, pittied
and favour'd me. <hi>Lucander</hi> and my ſelfe came to
the ſtate of youth; I, as being the leſſe fortunate,
was more beloved of the people; he of my Father,
as heire to the Monarchy: Thus farre I cannot ſay
I was very unhappy, for if he may juſtly bee called
ſo who is borne indiſcreet, and lives hated <hi>Lucan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
was the leſſe fortunate; but the originall of all
my afflictions was the faire <hi>Polixena,</hi> at the ſame
time brought up at Court, daughter to the Prince
<hi>Saga,</hi> one of great power, and neare allyed to the
King, without whoſe adviſe he undertook nothing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:114828:31"/>
of weight: I would diſcourſe more largely of her
beauty and perfections, if my love would not make
that ſeem paſſion, which heaven and my ſelfe know
is but truth. I ſpeake to a woman, and ſuch heare
with ſmall delight the prayſes of others: She was
the faireſt in that Conntrey, and from our tender
yeares, wee began to court her: I with leſſe hope
then <hi>Lucander,</hi> as one not borne a Prince: but
Love both a childe, and blinde, often miſtakes and
ſtumbles. I did ill to ſay my birth was attended by
no happie fortune, ſince <hi>Polixena</hi> fixed her eyes on
me, and that ſo freely, that whatſoever I did ſhee
graced with eſteeme, whatſoever my brother
attempted diſpleaſed her. At the publike and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne
Exerciſes, her favourable eyes encouraged
mee, and made me ſucceſſefull, not without the
envy of many Princes that ador'd her, eſpecially
of <hi>Lucander:</hi> truly I had the advantage of him
in behaviour, diſcretion, and ſtature; yet few wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
would have conſider'd thoſe accidents, the
qualities of the minde being in little eſteem in the
unfortunate. But <hi>Polixena</hi> either leſſe ambitious,
or more unhappy, inclin'd her affection to mee ſo
farre, that after a long time ſhe gave me leave to
obtaine her embraces, which by a private way in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
her chamber I enjoy'd: <hi>Lucander</hi> had treated
with her Father about marriage, engaging him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
ſtill further in his fond affection; knowing I
was his rivall, he was the more earneſt in his ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citation,
being vext to ſee <hi>Polixena</hi> prefer mee,
the illegitimate ſonne, before him the heire to the
Kingdome. Her Father (tranſported with his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:114828:31"/>
and hope of ſeeing the Crowne upon his
Daughters head) being diſpleas'd with my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
lookt not favorably on me, and chid <hi>Polixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi>
adviſing her to love <hi>Lucander;</hi> becauſe from
thence more good then ſhe imagin'd might reſult.
But this counſell was vaine; her election was no
longer free; much leſſe when ſhe perceiv'd ſhee
was with childe. This confirmation of our love en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd
my Obligation, and her danger: for this
Diſeaſe being difficult to conceale, and her Father
unwilling ſhe ſhould bee mine, we had reaſon to
feare the event: ſhe diſſembled the miſhap ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
that not any of her ſervants ſuſpected it. The
perplexity wherin I remain'd was as of one that ſees
his Love in the power of enemies: If ſhe would
have ſent me the childe, ſhe durſt not; for <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cander</hi>
had gained all or the moſt part of them to be
of his party. Thus every moment did theſe feares
diſquiet us, till one night ſuch extremity of paine
wakened her, that ſhe preſently knew the reaſon,
and putting on her cloathes in haſte, ſhe went out
at the back gate of the garden, (having before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
her ſelfe of the key for that occaſion) with
intent to retire to an houſe of an intimate friend of
mine, whom we had made acquainted with our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires:
but ſhe had ſcarce paſt two ſtreets when ſhe
was ſo ſurpriz'd that ſhee could not ſtirre a ſtep fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
turning aſide into the Porch of the next houſe,
was there delivered of a Daughter; and ſeeing two
men paſſe by muffled in their Cloaks, ſhee called
to them, and delivered them the childe, deſiring
them, becauſe ſhee was a woman and alone, that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:114828:32"/>
they would doe her the favour to carry it to <hi>Geſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menes</hi>
the Kings ſonne, who would give them a
better reward then they imagin'd: Their Civilitie
oblig'd them not to follow her; ſo ſhee return'd
back to the Court, and within two houres was laid
againe in her bed, where complaining of a ſuddain
indiſpoſition, ſhee was attended and ſerv'd as one,
whom all hop'd ere long to ſee their Queen.</p>
               <p>But ſo unfortunate was my affection and <hi>Polixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's</hi>
honour, that one of thoſe to whom ſhee had
deliver'd the childe was <hi>Lucander</hi> my brother and
enemy; who deviſing with himſelfe who the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of it might be, and ſeeing that <hi>Polixena</hi> fell
ſick that very night, begun to think it was ſhe; her
extraordinary affection to mee, making any conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture
ſeem credible; the childs countenance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd
this ſuſpition, which like a Coppy could not
deny the originall: Wherefore to revenge his jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie,
and to puniſh my boldneſſe, hee reſolv'd to
tell my Father, and my Wives, (for ſo I muſt call
her ſo long as I live) what had happened; firſt
commanding one of his ſervants to cut the child
in pieces, hee ſent it mee in performance of the
promiſe he had made the night before. As I was in
the morning making my ſelfe ready, there came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
my Chamber a Gentlewoman of great truſt with
<hi>Lucander,</hi> and a Page bearing in a Baſon the body
of the little childe, ſo pierced with wounds, that
the features of the face could hardly bee diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Thou maiſt imagine <hi>Iſmenia</hi> how I receiv'd
this Preſent: My heart was inſtantly congeal'd at
the bold impiety of <hi>Lucander,</hi> I then foreſaw my
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:114828:32"/>
misfortune, and mixing a Fathers teares with the yet
warme bloud, I bath'd the mangled Limbes; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling
my paſſion as well as I could, I went to
ſee him, and asked him the reaſon of ſo ſtrange a
Preſent, which would have moved feare and pitty
in the moſt cruell breaſt. My treacherous brother,
as if he had done me an extraordinary favour, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
the ſad accident, and told me his deſigne to
ruine me, and perſecute the afflicted <hi>Polixena.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p> It
is not poſſible (replyed I) hee can bee of noble
bloud that glories in ſuch baſe attempts. There is
no reaſon to embolden thee to injure my life and
ſoule, but the lowneſſe of my condition; if it were
otherwiſe, I would make thee feele my anger; if
my love diſpleas'd thee, and thou wert jealous, why
doſt thou not like a man rather kil me, then revenge
thy ſelfe on a thing that had neither hands nor
tongue to defend it ſelfe: But thou art ſo baſe a
Coward, that thou feareſt mee, though of a deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable
fortune: from henceforward thou ſhalt have
more cauſe to do ſo: for I will ſurprize thy life
when thou leaſt ſuſpect'ſt it: But heaven I believe
not uſing to remit the puniſhment of ſuch wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe
to the next life, will prevent me in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge
of that innocent bloud. <hi>Lucander</hi> knew not
what to anſwer to ſo juſt an accuſation, but began
to reproach my birth, ſaying, that his Mother not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
was free from infamy. And as ſons are
moſt ſenſible of thoſe injuries, though truths, that
reflect on their Parents, I was ſo full of paſſion that
the leaſt occaſion would have tranſported m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
reaſon, and drawing my Sword I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:114828:33"/>
him before he could cry out for help or defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
and left him wounded, &amp; weltring in his own
bloud; with this the Court was in a tumult, and
the news coming to the King my Fathers eare,
he commanded that they ſhould ſeize on mee, and
teare me in pieces; but eſcaping from the ſwords of
thoſe that purſued me, I took horſe and fled into the
covert of this mountaine, till my enemies had loſt
ſight of me. After two dayes I arriv'd at this ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
place, where, to defend my ſelfe from the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
of the night, I made uſe of the ſhelter of this
Cave, and being overcome with wearineſſe, I ſlept
till the day following: So ſoon as the Sun enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
this wood, awaking I ſaw a fierce Lyon lying
at my feet, who having found mee aſleep, either
imagining I was dead, or complying with his native
generoſitie, granted me my life (for there is even in
the moſt ſavage Beaſts, a kind of naturall pitty) and
not onely forbare to doe me hurt, but by fawning,
and other expreſſions of love, ſeem'd to court me.
Though the ſociety were dangerous, my life being at
all times in his power: I conſidered that my life was
without doubt reſerv'd, for ſome extraordinary end,
ſince heaven had preſerv'd it from ſo many chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.
Having found more kindneſſe in a Lyon then
in a Father or Brother I made much of him, which
he requites with his uſual bringing me in his mouth
the prey that he hath kill'd, to ſuſtaine my life, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
me rather his companion then enemy. Within
a yeare I was ſo much maſter of theſe Mountaines,
Cliffs, and beaſts, that all obey'd mee, like the firſt
man, and for this reaſon would I not leave this
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:114828:33"/>
place; in another I muſt meet my death: for the
injuries that are done to the powerfull cannot (but
miraculouſly) eſcape unreveng'd.</p>
               <p>Inſtead of a Palace I have here a ſecure, though
poore dwelling; for a guard of ſouldiers two Lions
to protect me: theſe Hives offer me honey; this ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
water; theſe mountaines a ſhady Covert; and
theſe Trees their wilde fruits: The Beaſts that I kill
afford me cloathing, the Sea fiſh, and the Woods ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſon:
This is my life and ſtory; ſo that if thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve
to continue here, I promiſe to entertaine thee
with as much care, as if thou wert my deare wife,
or poore daughter, whoſe face I never ſaw, though
I once handled it. Thou ſhalt have a freſh and ſweet
bed made of Ruſhes, Flags, and Thyme; in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
wee will ſhelter our ſelves in the Bowells of this
Rock, and in ſummer thou ſhalt enjoy the pleaſant
Weſt winde, underneath the ſhade of theſe Hazell
Trees: my diſpoſition is gentle, my birth ſuch as
thou haſt heard, and from this minute I ſweare ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
to offend thy chaſtity ſo much as in a thought.
We will ſpend the morning in praiſing heaven, that
figuring it ſelfe in all its Creatures hath inrich'd a
meane Shepherdeſſe with ſuch perfections. The
Evenings we will viſit this Grove from whence we
will borrow Bowes for fuell and light: The time
that wee ſave from ſleep wee will ſpend in relating
our paſt misfortunes, and by this meanes I may
beguile my love, imagining that <hi>Polixena</hi> dwells
with me: for thou ſo nearely reſembleſt her, that
Heaven ſeemes to have made thy Beauty as a coppy
of hers.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:114828:34"/>
Here <hi>Geſimenes</hi> ſtopt (for the remembrance of
his wife drew teares from his eyes) and <hi>Iſmenia</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
to him, comforted him, promiſing not to be a
minute from his ſide; for beſides that his perſon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
it, a naturall inclination induc'd her to eſteem,
and to give him as much reſpect as if he were her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
ſo that to divert ſome part of his griefes,
ſhee took out of her Scrip an inſtrument, and ſung
thus:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Narciſſa</hi> paſſing through a pleaſant Mead,</l>
               <l>To coole her thirſt was to a River led:</l>
               <l>When ſhe perceiv'd the lazie ſtreame had loſt</l>
               <l>Its courſe, condens'd to Chriſtall by the Froſt;</l>
               <l>Which had perhaps enamour'd of her ſight,</l>
               <l>Begg'd of <hi>December</hi> chains to ſtop its flight;</l>
               <l>But the kinde Sun did with his warmer beames,</l>
               <l>Diſſolve the Ice into its native ſtreames:</l>
               <l>And th' angry little Brook, deny'd by ſtay,</l>
               <l>Was enjoy'd flying, wept, and went away.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The company of <hi>Iſmenia</hi> was an extraordinarie
comfort to <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> who recreated by her beauty
and wit paſſed the houres of the day with leſſe anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
loving each other with ſo true yet chaſte affection
as they never entertain'd one looſe thought. Thus
lived they both ſecure and contented, eſpecially <hi>Iſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi>
becauſe ſhee was not in love, nor acquainted
with any cares that might diſquiet her reſt. But ſhe
could not long boaſt her liberty: for as one after-noon
ſhe beheld her ſelfe in that Chriſtall Rivolet, when
the dying Sunne was giving up his languiſhing light,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:114828:34"/>
ſhe ſpied a young Gentleman who wearied in the
purſute of ſome wilde beaſt, having left his horſe,
ſlept upon the Flowers, (leaning his cheek on his
hand) to the ſweet Muſick which the water made,
playing with the blew pebbles. Having earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held
him, (for his perſon was warlike, his apparell
Majeſtick, &amp; his forme Divine;) ſhe would have gone
away, but could not; for love ſeizeth on free hearts,
and like a flaſh of lightning ſuddenly ſcorches. In
briefe, <hi>Iſmenia</hi> found her feet fetter'd, and her ſoule
inclined to ſtay. Thus ſuffering her ſelfe to bee van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh'd
by love, ſhe ſoftly approached him, and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the ſword that hung in his Scarffe, ſuddenly
awaked him, bidding him receive it, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
that he owed his life to her, who could ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily
have taken it. <hi>Perozes</hi> (for that was his name)
ſtarting up, and admiring <hi>Iſmenias</hi> exquiſite beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
anſwered,<q> that he could not thank her pitty for
not giving him death by the ſword, if he muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
it from her eyes; that ſhe expreſſed thus more
cruelty then mercy, for aſleep he ſhould not have
been ſenſible of the one, but it was impoſſible for
him waking to eſcape the other.</q> Her habit caus'd
in him no leſſe wonder then her beauty, wherefore
he beſought her by entreaties and promiſes to tell
him the reaſon why ſhe liv'd in that Mountaine, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richt
with perfections that might become a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace;
unleſſe ſhe were ſome new <hi>Diana,</hi> ſome divine
Huntreſſe, who diſdaining to live amongſt men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
to ſpend her time in that wilderneſſe. <hi>Iſmenia</hi>
reply'd, that ſhe came thither to accompany her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
one of a noble birth, and excellent qaalities,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:114828:35"/>
though throwne down by fortune to a low eſtate,
They were both as much intangled in love as if they
had convers'd together many yeares, each of them ſo
delighted with the others company, that <hi>Iſmenia</hi> had
no power to retire up the Mountaine to <hi>Geſimenes,</hi>
nor <hi>Perozes</hi> to deſcend to the valley to ſeek his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,
whom that afternoon hee had loſt in the
chace: but the diſcreet Shepherdneſſe ſeeing the night
threaten them, and being farre from home, thus ſpake
unto him:</p>
            <q>
               <p>Sir, I would to heaven, as you have engag'd my
affection, ſo I had worth to deſerve yours; yet if
love be begotten by ſympathy of bloud, what I
have ſeen in your ſuſpence, your eyes and words,
may at the leaſt bee good will: and that you may
not thinke I participate of the rudeneſſe of this
place, I will ſometimes deſcend to this ſeat, where
you may ſee mee, with this caution, that you offer
me no injurie: That would be both dishonourable
and unſafe; For my Father will at my call come
downe, and to ſecond him a Lion to teare you in
pieces.</p>
               <p>It ſeemes (anſwered <hi>Perozes</hi>) you doe not know
me, ſeeing with ſuch unneceſſary care you inſtruct
me in a reſpect that I am oblig'd to keep for both our
ſakes: Yours, becauſe I adore you, and he that loves
cannot injure; my owne, becauſe my birth is noble,
which it could not be, if I had a deſire to tyrannize
over women. When heaven hath cloath'd the night
with Stars I will come hither with as much humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
as love, and adore theſe Flowers, becauſe you
have trod on them, and this River becauſe it hath
been your glaſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:114828:35"/>
With this they tooke leave of each other. The
affection of <hi>Iſmenia</hi> dayly encreas'd ſo much
that <hi>Geſimenes</hi> might eaſily have perceived it,
if hee had ſuſpected there had beene more men
in the wood to converſe with: nor was <hi>Perozes</hi>
her debtour; for every houre of the day ſhee was in
his mind, and the nights he waited in the Mountaine
expecting her; though ſhe could not come downe
ſo often as ſhee would; for <hi>Geſimenes</hi> had chid her
for comming home ſo late, little ſuſpecting love
to be the cauſe, but rather her eagerneſſe of the
chaſe.</p>
            <p>Upon a time ſhee came thither unobſerv'd by <hi>Geſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menes,</hi>
and caſting her eye aſide found in a crimſon
Taffata a Picture of a faire Lady wrapt up in Paper,
which ſerv'd for its caſe: this it ſeemes <hi>Perozes</hi> had
through negligence the night before let fall amongſt
the Jeſmines: <hi>Iſmenia</hi> perceiving the Inſcription
was directed to him, moved with the curioſity of a
jealous woman, read it, and found it ſaid thus:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am now come to <hi>Albania,</hi> where I
live privately, and have ſeen the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe,
whoſe beautie I here ſend you drawn
in this Tablet, though it be ſo excellent,
that theſe Colours doe but injure it. May
I know your pleaſure that I may haſten
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:114828:36"/>
my journey, and the contract of theſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
Nuptialls, whereby the warres that
have long infeſted both Kingdomes may
have an end.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſmenia</hi> would not proceed any further, nor indeed
could ſhee for jealouſie and anger; a leſſe diſcovery
might have been ſufficient to have kill'd her: ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed
her malicious fortune, and much bewailed the
loſſe of <hi>Perozes,</hi> apprehending ſo many inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
that it ſeemed impoſſible he ſhould ever bee
hers. Firſt, his Birth, and the diſtance between them;
next, hee was to marry a Princeſſe, enrich'd (as
the Picture ſhew'd) with extraordinary beauty; but
hearing ſome body come, ſhe diſſembled her griefe,
and perceiv'd it was her Enemy, who (as hee came
along) ſung thus:</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>As faire <hi>Iſmenia</hi> forth did goe,</l>
                  <l>A Saphire ſparkled in each eye,</l>
                  <l>And on her cheek did Jeſmines grow,</l>
                  <l>Bath'd in the Roſes Purple dye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But when I nearer came t'have plaid</l>
                  <l>Within the Sun-ſhine of her light,</l>
                  <l>She ſcorc'd me, in her beames betraid</l>
                  <l>Like ſportive flyes to loſſe of ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:114828:36"/>
                  <l>What feare and reverence doth beget</l>
                  <l>Th' approach unto ſo bright a flame,</l>
                  <l>Which can extinguiſh with its heate,</l>
                  <l>And makes both love and death the ſame!</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>An injur'd woman is not ſenſible of any thing ſo
much as of flattery from him that wrongs her; and
<hi>Iſmenia</hi> confident that <hi>Perozes</hi> love was counterfeit,
tooke it more unkindly to bee deceiv'd, then unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited;
for diſaffection may bee naturall, and out of
our power, but diſſimulation is not, being bred onely
in malicious breaſts. That <hi>Perozes</hi> might not boaſt he
had forſaken her firſt, though for the Princeſſe of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania,</hi>
ſhe went to him, and betwixt reaſon and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie
ſaid thus:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Perozes,</hi> though you ſee mee in this Mountaine,
ſo rudely attir'd, that my richeſt ornament is the
ſpotted skin of a Tygreſſe, yet you may well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
my ſoul hath more worth then my habit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth.
You ſay you love me ſo infinitely, that
though you are of the beſt bloud in <hi>Armenia,</hi> yet
you will hazard both life &amp; fortune to be my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band;
and as this expreſſion muſt not either by the
Laws of Civility or affection be unacknowledged, I
requited it with the like. But as thoſe that love can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
diſſemble, (for that's a crime) it grieves my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
to have hid a ſecret from you. It is impoſſible
wee ſhould ever enjoy each other. Do not wonder
that I undeceive you now, whereas I might as well
have done it before. All women at firſt conceale their
paſſions, unwilling to diſcover their imperfections
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:114828:37"/>
to them they know not; for by open profeſſion of
love they might beget too ſlight an opinion of
themſelves; but when we find engagement wee
have a care to diſcover the truth to ſuch Profeſſors
of affection, that they may ſee the danger they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre,
either for avoidance or excuſe. The ſumme of
all is to let you know I am anothers; he who I told
you was my Father, is not ſo, but one whom miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune
hath baniſh'd <hi>Albania,</hi> and he has my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
to be his wife, though in truth he hath yet had
no other aſſurance then my hand; therefore love
me leſſe, and containe your ſelfe more: my deſcent
is noble, and I muſt be his, having once profeſt it;
for my Obligation cannot be diſcharg'd but by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
my ſelfe unto him, and he is of ſo excellent
and gallant a mind that he (thinke it not paſſion)
ſurpaſſeth you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Scarſe had the jealous <hi>Iſmenia</hi> ended, when with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
expecting an anſwer of ſatisfaction, ſhee ran a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
into the more envious part of the Wilderneſſe;
<hi>Perozes</hi> being unacquainted with the place preſently
loſt her, expreſſing ſo much paſſion as might have
mollifi'd a Rock, if it could have heard him; but all
in vaine; <hi>Iſmenia</hi> would not runne the hazard of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting
by hearing what hee could ſay: for the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
diſpoſition of women is perſwaded to weepe by
ſeeing others do ſo: yet was ſhe not without reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
for, retiring to the remoteſt corner of the
Cave ſhee wept affectionate teares, and taking out
the Letter that was directed to her lover, ſhee kiſt
that name in the ſuperſcription which was engraved
in her heart. Thus the two Lovers paſſed two dayes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:114828:37"/>
without meeting, not through <hi>Perozes</hi> neglect, but
<hi>Iſmenia's</hi> obſtinacy, who ſaying late one evening at
the border of the mountaine to behold a tree, on
whoſe barke both their names were engraven:
<q>What availes it (ſaid ſhee complaining to her ſelfe)
that <hi>Peroſes</hi> writeth himſelfe mine on the trees,
when the Princeſſe of <hi>Albania</hi> may countermand
it? what that he flatters mee with ſuch kinde affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
in this ſolitude, if at Court he adores a brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
beauty?</q> ſhee would have ſaid more, had ſhee
not been interrupted by the Muſick of a ſweet voice
from amongſt the Poplars: though ſhe knew it was
her ungratefull Lover, yet ſhee was willing to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence
a little with her reſolution, and hearken to
this Song:</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iſmenia's</hi> eyes my ſoule divide,</l>
                  <l>A faire yet hapleſſe Sheperdeſſe,</l>
                  <l>In whom rich Nature all her pride,</l>
                  <l>And Fates their poverty expreſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To move the ſute I feare to miſſe</l>
                  <l>Her worth and my reſpect deny;</l>
                  <l>For where even hope endanger'd is,</l>
                  <l>Lovers in ſilence uſe to dye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus the deſire I entertaine,</l>
                  <l>Neither ſhuns love, nor ſute preferrs;</l>
                  <l>For though ſhe to be mine diſdaine,</l>
                  <l>I'me bleſt enough in being hers.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:114828:38"/>
               <hi>Iſmenia</hi> perceiving by the words and voice it was
<hi>Perozes,</hi> ſought to hide her ſelfe in the buſhes, that
ſhe might avoid ſight and ſpeech with him; not that
ſhe was averſe from it, but ſhe would not give occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
to awake that love which ſlumbred in abſence;
but the ruſhing of the leaves betraid her: <hi>Perozes</hi> told
her, <q>She had no reaſon (unleſſe ſhe had with her
habit changed he humanity) to fly from one who
had not loſt her through any offence of his own:
But ſince he was ſo unfortunat, that he could not
be hers, he entreated her to informe her ſelfe by
that Paper of his extreme paſſion, that ſhe might
at leaſt know how much ſhe was indebted to him:</q>
ſo taking leave of her, he left in her hand theſe
Verſes, which ſhe imprinted as ſhe read them in her
ſoule.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Divineſt Syren, cruell faire;</l>
               <l>Cauſe of my life, and my deſpaire;</l>
               <l>Griefe that deſcends to words is weake;</l>
               <l>But mine is full and cannot ſpeake:</l>
               <l>For how can Fate more cruell be,</l>
               <l>Then to grant life, denying thee?</l>
               <l>Yet I in death hope to adore</l>
               <l>Thoſe joyes without which life is poore:</l>
               <l>My reaſon's baniſh'd by my paine;</l>
               <l>Who can loſe thee, and it retaine?</l>
               <l>How ſoon was my calme ſoule dejected,</l>
               <l>And ruine ſuffer'd ere expected!</l>
               <l>But ſince that bliſſe which once was mine,</l>
               <l>Thou to another wilt reſigne.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:114828:38"/>
Be happy in thy choice; whilſt I</l>
               <l>In unregarded aſhes lye</l>
               <l>Be happy in him; 'tis unfit</l>
               <l>To wiſh thee joy and hinder it.</l>
               <l>Then finiſh what thou haſt begun,</l>
               <l>Encreaſe my griefe, and kill me ſoon.</l>
               <l>And when I'me dead let pitty move thee,</l>
               <l>But to remember I did love thee.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſmenia</hi> relenting would have read them often, had
ſhee not beene hindred by <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> who comming
to ſeek her, and glad to have found her, entreated her
to divert his continuall Melancholy with a Song;
whereupon, more to obey him then pleaſe her ſelfe,
(diſſembling her griefe) ſhe ſung thus:</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why doth that foole unjuſtly love accuſe,</l>
                  <l>Who through his owne feare did occaſion loſe?</l>
                  <l>To miſſe an offer'd happineſse muſt be,</l>
                  <l>Or want of love, or too much modeſty:</l>
                  <l>Thy ſcorne <hi>Lyſarda</hi> I have juſtly won,</l>
                  <l>Who wanted light when I embrac'd the Sun.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O look into my heart, thou wilt ſee there,</l>
                  <l>'Twas admiration onely caus'd my feare:</l>
                  <l>Reſpect curb'd my affection; let me dye,</l>
                  <l>(diſpleaſing thee) by thy enflaming eye:</l>
                  <l>Such death will make thy cruelty confeſſe,</l>
                  <l>I never wanted love, though happineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>When <hi>Iſmenia</hi> had ended her Song, it being late,
they retired homewards; and as they were going up
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:114828:39"/>
the Hill, by a Lane fenced on either ſide with Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes
and white Poplars, they heard a great ſound
as of ſomething that fell from an high; <hi>Iſmenia</hi> was
amazed, and <hi>Geſimenes</hi> laid hold of his Bow, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
it might be ſome wild beaſt; they ſearched all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout,
but could not find the cauſe; at laſt they percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
a Barke (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o they were not far from the Sea)
neare the Shore; it was covered over, and had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Helme nor Mariner to guide it; <hi>Geſimenes</hi> and
<hi>Iſmenia</hi> faſtned it to Land, and were deſirous to know
what was in it; ſcarce were the Sailes and Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
taken off, when ſuch aſtoniſhment ſeiz'd them,
that for a good ſpace they did nothing but looke on
each other: within it was a man bathed in bloud,
and by his ſid a beautiful Lady, living, yet ſo diſmaid,
that ſhe wanted little of the dead body which lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide
her: They were both afflicted at ſo ſad a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle,
eſpecially <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> who intentively behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Lady, fancied, he ſaw in her the face and
perſon of his abſent Wife. He gave the dead body
buriall in the Sea, ſince there was no meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore
his life: he tooke the Lady in his armes, and
carried her to the homely Palace of his Cave, where
he entertain'd her with ſuch care, that in a ſhort time
he had good hope of her life.</p>
            <p>When ſhe had recovered ſo much ſtrength as to
open her eyes, and found on either ſide of her a man
and woman: At firſt ſhe was afraid of them, though
their behaviour and hoſpitality had expreſt more pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
then her ſevere father and kindred: She wondred
much that <hi>Geſimenes</hi> ſo conſtantly fixed his eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
her; and hearing <hi>Iſmenia</hi> ſometimes call him
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:114828:39"/>
by his name, ſhe ſaid to him. <q>Two things hold mee
in this ſuſpence, you may do me a favour to inſtruct
me in them: Is it true that you are called <hi>Geſimenes?</hi>
Why ſince I opened my eyes have you ſo ſtedfaſtly
beheld me, often ſighing, and ſometimes weeping?
you may aske the ſame of mee, becauſe when I firſt
heard your name, it ſtruck mee to the ſoule; For I
loved a Gentleman of the ſame name, at the expence
of ſo many afflictions, that this hazard of my life
was the leaſt; and ſhould I ſay, that this <hi>Geſimenes</hi>
(whom I call Husband) was ſon to the King of
<hi>Albania,</hi> truth would not accuſe me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geſimenes</hi> was ſo tranſported with joy, that hee
could ſcarce expreſſe his mind. <q>If (ſaid hee) I
am the unfortunate Sonne of <hi>Pharnazes,</hi> and thy
Husband; if thou art <hi>Polixena,</hi> and my eyes deceive
me not, how can I behold thee without an extaſie
of content? how can my heart but breake with the
apprehenſion of the misfortunes thou haſt ſuffered
for my ſake? <hi>Polixena,</hi> I am <hi>Geſimenes;</hi> and will be
thine, till heaven deprive me of this life, which I
eſteem now I enjoy thy ſight and embraces. Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward
I ſhall deſire life, which I thought I ſhould
never have done: for during the time I have dwelt
among theſe Rocks, the riſing Sunne never found
mee not ſuing to heaven to be eaſed of it; for life
is not a pleaſure, but a torment to the unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Words are not full enough to expreſſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
of theſe two Lovers; for language is too narrow
to cloath great paſſions; ſo that with their eyes and
ſoules they congratulated their ſtrange and happy
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:114828:40"/>
meeting. The beauty of <hi>Iſmenia</hi> and <hi>Geſimenes</hi> care
of her, might well have given <hi>Polixena</hi> cauſe of jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie;
yet when ſhee was informed of the occaſion
which brought her to live with him, ſhee eſteemed
her with as much affection as if ſhee had beene her
owne daughter. Thus being all three equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented,
<hi>Geſimenes</hi> deſired her to inſtruct them in the
afflictions ſhee ſuffered during his abſence: for the
relation of paſt miſeries in proſperity doth deiight
more then diſconſolate: wherefore to comply with
their requeſt, ſhe ſaid:</p>
            <q>
               <p>So many, my deare <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> have been the
troubles that oppreſt me in your abſence, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall,
that 'tis impoſſible I ſhould either then have
reſented them, or now relate them fully. I was left
as your ſurety, to ſatisfie the hurt you did <hi>Lucander;</hi>
who ſeeing hee could not revenge himſelfe on you,
reſolv'd to do it on your other ſelfe, divulging my
weakneſſe, and giving it out that I was delivered
in his armes: My Father inſtead of puniſhing the
infamous cruelty he uſed to the innocent Infant, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting
the relation it had to his bloud, encouraged
him, and commanded I ſhould bee ſhut up in a
Tower, where for a long time I neither ſaw the face
of the Sun, or of any humane creature; untill at
laſt the King your Father mov'd with pitty, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
one that had been brought up in my Fathers
houſe to viſit mee, for they repoſed truſt in him.
With him I recreated the tedious houres of my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment,
relating to him my misfortunes. One
day hee telling me that you were for certaine in a
Village neare <hi>Albania,</hi> I earneſtly begg'd of him to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:114828:40"/>
afford mee ſome private meanes of writing to
you, which he did: Then did I ſigne the death
of us both; For I writ a Letter, wherein I informed
you of my ſad condition, and of the great affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the people to you, who continually pittied
you as much as they wiſht <hi>Lucanders</hi> death, for
being poſſeſt of the Crowne, he oppreſt them
with tyrannicall injuries. I adviſed you to make uſe
of the protection of ſome other Prince, by whoſe
aid you might compaſſe your revenge; In the mean
time, that I would (if it were needfull) poyſon the
Prince, that the Subjects ſeeing him dead, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
you were alive, might be neceſſitated to ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
you, lawfully to poſſeſſe the Kingdome after the
deceaſe of <hi>Pharnazes.</hi> Theſe, and other things of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance
did I write in that unhappy Letter, to eaſe
my heart, and redreſſe your miſeries; but there is no
ſucceſſe where Fate oppoſeth; ſo unfortunate were
<hi>Arneſtes</hi> and I, that as he went from my chamber
to ſeeke you out, he met <hi>Lucander,</hi> who queſtioned
him concerning me; whereupon he was ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded,
that your Brother began to ſuſpect ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
and cauſing him to be apprehended and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,
found this Letter, by which he confeſt more
then he knew: this put the Court into a tumult. My
Father (who would be ſingular in Loyalty, though
at the expence of my life) executed on me the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
cruelty the world ever ſaw. He gave order
for a Barke, ſo cloſed that the aire had no paſsage;
into which, having kill'd poore <hi>Arneſtes</hi> with many
wounds, he ſhut him dead, and me alive, to the
intent that I might with the horrour miſerably end
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:114828:41"/>
my life. Then ſetting the Barke a drift, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
us to the mercy of the waves, pitied of as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
as beheld us. Thus we floated until heaven (mov'd
with my prayers and teares) was pleas'd to caſt me
on this ſhore, where your care hath brought me once
more into the light, and reſtored that happineſſe
which from my infancy I deſir'd, though it hath coſt
me ſo deare.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſmenia</hi> and <hi>Geſimenes</hi> congratulated <hi>Polixena's</hi>
good fortune; for though it were Eclips'd with trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
and diſcontents, yet the event being happy
it cannot be called adverſe. Thus lived <hi>Geſimenes</hi>
with his wife more contented then if he had been
Lord of the whole world, enjoying her beauty and
company without feare or interruption, endearing
to himſelfe that bleſſing which heaven after ſo many
yeares of affliction had reſerv'd for him. <hi>Iſmenia</hi>
and <hi>Perozes</hi> paſt the time with leſſe delight, complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
each of the others affection; ſhe as thinking he
was contracted to another, and he as having the ſame
opinion of her: But <hi>Iſmenia</hi> weary of concealing
her jealouſie, was unwilling that <hi>Perozes</hi> ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
her of inconſtancy, when ſhe had juſt cauſe to
condemne him: wherefore ſhe found him out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
the Lawrels and Jeſmines, and ſhewed him
the Pictnre and Letter: She told him, <q>That the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
why ſhe had belied her own affection and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy,
was not that ſhe lov'd any elſe, but that ſhe
was of opinion he was anothers; that thoſe two
witneſses would prove it &amp; that he could not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
at her cruelty, ſince his falſehood and ill requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
deſerved it.</q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:114828:41"/>
I confeſs (faire <hi>Iſmenia</hi>) replyed <hi>Perozes,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I ſaw you, I treated of a marriage with the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
of <hi>Albania;</hi> but I aſſure you, after I beheld your
divine beauty, and beleeved that I had obtained ſome
place in your affection, I alterd my reſolution
(though to the diſcontent of my Father and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
who earneſtly deſire the accompliſhment of that
match, to put an end to the wars between the two
kingdoms) To comply with your affection, I engage
my faith never to marry as long as I live, unleſſe
with you; nor ſhall you be, (if the ſtories ſay true) the
firſt Queen that was bred up amongſt Woods and
Rocks; but be ſure that he, whom you call your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
be ſo indeed; for if you deceive me, and he prove
a Lover, I will ſo revenge my ſelfe on both, that my
love ſhall wonder at my ſeverity.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſmenia</hi> was ſo well ſatisfied and pleas'd with <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rozes</hi>
promiſe, that to confirme what ſhee had ſaid,
ſhe plac'd him ſo, that he might ſee <hi>Geſimenes</hi> in his
Wives armes; and as Lovers ſeldome conceale
any thing from one another, notwithſtanding ſhe
had told him that he was her Father, ſhee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
to him their true ſtory; to which <hi>Perozes</hi>
hearken'd with much content, ſeeing how nobly his
beloved <hi>Iſmenia</hi> was deſcended if <hi>Geſimenes</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixena</hi>
were her Parents, for then ſhe was Neece
to the King of <hi>Albania,</hi> a good reaſon to excuſe his
unadviſed love, ſince he married, though not the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,
yet one of her bloud. With theſe joyful hopes <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rozes</hi>
took his leave, but <hi>Iſmenia</hi> was troubled when
ſhe conſidered that ſhe had done ill to feigne her ſelfe
the daughter of <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> knowing how eaſie it
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:114828:42"/>
was to diſprove it: for though her affection and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance
made it probable, yet ſhe was conſcious
that their births were extremely different.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Perozes,</hi> devoting himſelf wholly to the affection of
<hi>Iſmenia,</hi> and reſolving to marry her, refus'd the match
with the Princeſſe of <hi>Albania,</hi> and ſent to give
<hi>Pharnazes</hi> notice he was already married, who was
ſenſible of this affront, believing that this neglect was
in contempt of his alliance; and without expecting
either Letters or Ambaſſadors, with his Son <hi>Lucan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
he raiſed a great Army, binding themſelves by a
ſolemne Oath not to return to <hi>Albania,</hi> till they had
either taken or ſlaine <hi>Perozes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other ſide <hi>Perozes</hi> was not negligent;
for having notice of the intention of <hi>Pharnazes,</hi> he
deſired of his Father a Commiſſion for that Warre,
and leavied ſufficient forces to reſiſt the proud <hi>Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi>
Meane while, viſiting <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> he deſired her
to perſwade her Father <hi>Geſimenes</hi> (who was a great
Souldier) to command his Army; as well to protect
the cauſe which was his owne, being his daughters,
as to revenge himſelfe upon <hi>Lucander,</hi> who now came
inſolently with <hi>Pharnazes;</hi> beſides the <hi>Albanians</hi>
might hereby know he was alive, and had power to
oppoſe them. <hi>Iſmenia</hi> was much perplext to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee
her impoſture would be ſoone diſcovered; but
committing all to time and fortune, ſhe determined
to ſpeake to <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> and thereupon informed him
of the Princes affection, the occaſion of the Warre,
and the opportunity which heaven hath offer'd him
to returne from that miſerable kind of life to his firſt
eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:114828:42"/>
               <hi>Geſimenes</hi> diſliked not the meanes which <hi>Iſmenia</hi>
in <hi>Perozes</hi> name offered for obtaining the deſired
end of his affaires. Hee was willing to ſerve him;
but not therby to injure his father: a relation (though
hee were ungratefull) not to bee diſpenc'd with. His
hope was to bee the inſtrument of peace, and of the
death of his treacherous brother, upon whoſe death
he might returne to <hi>Albania</hi> and enjoy the Crowne.
<hi>Iſmenia</hi> told him, that it would be requiſite for ſome
time to acknowledge her for his daughter. <hi>Geſime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi>
reply'd, that he ſhould not onely for a time, but
as long as he lived eſteeme her ſo: For the love he bare
her, and the reſemblance ſhee had to <hi>Polixena</hi> was
ſuch, that if her Parentage had not been very meane,
it would eaſily have bin credited. <hi>Iſmenia</hi> brought him
to <hi>Perozes,</hi> the two Princes convers'd together with
great expreſſions of affection. <hi>Perozes</hi> wondred to
behold him ſo alter'd and different from what he had
known him before; and enquiring after <hi>Polixena,</hi> he
intreated him to bring her along that ſhe might beare
his ſiſter company. They were honourably received
by the Nobility and commons of that Kingdome,
with reſpect due to perſons of ſuch eminence. The
King conferred the Generalls Staffe on <hi>Geſimenes,</hi>
who changing his Habit, appear'd ſo gracefull and
majeſtick, that they could hardly perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
hee was the ſame whom the day before they
had ſeen in that wilde ſhape: ſo much do ornaments
adde to exteriour Beauty.</p>
            <p>By this time the proud <hi>Albanians</hi> were come ſo
neare, that the mountaines reſounded with the eccho
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:114828:43"/>
of their Warlike inſtruments: At night <hi>Geſimenes</hi>
went out in his old habit, to eſpy in the Campe with
what force his father came; he was ſo well acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with that place that hee feared not to loſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
and wearing ſo ſtrange a habit it was impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
they ſhould ſuſpect him. One night as he went
downe from his Cave to the bottome of the Hill,
with intent to returne to the Court, hee heard ſome
not farre off conſulting privately together; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing
himſelfe behinde a tuft of Oakes and Pines,
hee beheld from them thence a young man in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour,
whom all the reſt ſeemed to reſpect and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
as their Maſter; <hi>Geſimenes</hi> by reaſon of the
darkneſſe of the night could not diſcern who he was,
but he gather'd that from his words, which ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
troubled him, for he was ſpeaking to them to this
effect:</p>
            <q>
               <p>Though here are but a few that heare mee, yet
I may well ſay here is the greateſt part of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
of <hi>Albania;</hi> for there is not any one can equall
<hi>Lucander,</hi> or ſtand in competition with you. I
am as you know, the Kings onely ſonne: for
though I lately had a Brother, I believe either the
Sea or Land by this time hath hid him in its Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells;
or if he were alive, yet being a Baſtard, hee
could not oppoſe me the lawfull Heire; nor hath
he the right I have. My Father is old, and uſeth
both you and mee too harſhly. Indeed I am ſorry
he hath liv'd thus long: It troubles me to be a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
being now fit for government, which ſo long
as he lives I cannot enjoy. I have at other times
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:114828:43"/>
adviſed with you about this buſineſs. The cauſe that
mov'd me now to call you together is an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
of effecting this deſigne, which offers it ſelfe
unto you. My Father is ſo induſtriouſly carefull in
this War, that though his years diſſwade him, he
often goeth forth alone to view both his own Camp
and the enemies. This night I eſpied him; and if I
miſtake not, he is now comming along that Path, ſo
that if you pleaſe now to follow me, we may this
very inſtant aſſault and kill him; and we will teare
his garments, that it may be thought the wild
Beaſts of theſe mountaines were his Murderers. The
Souldiers then being deſtitute of a King, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
transfer the Crown on me; of which when
I am poſſeſt, and the Scepter in my hand, I will by
degrees deſtroy all that favour'd <hi>Geſimenes.</hi> You ſhall
not be my Subjects but my friends, my companions,
on whoſe Shoulders I will lay the weight and care of
the whole Kingdom.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The Piety of <hi>Geſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>menes</hi> could ſcarce believe the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany
which <hi>Lucander</hi> intended againſt him to whom
he owed his being: but giving thanks to heaven for
the favourable opportunity of preſerving his Fathers
life, hee went that way by which <hi>Lucander</hi> ſaid hee
was to paſſe. He had not gone farre when hee found
him compleatly arm'd, going about to informe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
of the ſtate of the Camp, who ſeeing him drew his
ſword, thinking he was a wild man, &amp; aſſaulted him
to kil him: But <hi>Geſimenies</hi> in token of peace throwing
down the young Tree which he had in his hand, told
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:114828:44"/>
him that he might ſee he was a man as himſelfe, that
he came to adviſe him, not to go that way, becauſe
his ſonne with ſome of his Subjects, who it ſeemes
would be advantaged by his death, lay in wait to kill
him.</p>
            <q>
               <p>If thou doſt think, ſaid <hi>Pharnazes,</hi> by this deceit
to injure me, know thou art mistaken, for at my call
twenty thouſand men that I have in the field will
come forth, againſt whom neither thy ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
nor ſtrength can availe thee; beſides I am
able to defend my ſelfe not onely againſt thee (who
art a poore conqueſt) but againſt as many wilde
Beaſts as this Deſert nouriſhes.</p>
               <p>That you may be aſſured, (replyed <hi>Geſimenes</hi>)
I neither deceive, nor deſire to injure you, go down
by this little hill, &amp; you will ſee to whoſe truſt you
commit your ſelfe: be confident I would not ſuffer
you to paſſe any further, or conſent you ſhould put
your ſelfe into ſo imminent danger, were I not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
my owne ſtrength could ſufficiently, defend
you: Believe your ſelfe ſecure in my faith, for I
love you more then you imagine, though not out
of obligation, for you have uſed me with ſeverity, of
which ſome other occaſion ſhall informe you, if my
unfortunate ſtars permit.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharnazes</hi> was amazed at this Speech, and was the
ſooner enclined to credit it, when he cald to mind the
ill diſpoſition of <hi>Lucander,</hi> and ſome others that hee
convers'd with: he was unwilliug to returne to his
Tent before he had ſatisfied himſelfe; wherefore hee
deſcended the bottome of the Hill, and <hi>Geſimenes</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:114828:44"/>
after him, earneſtly deſiring the Traitors would ſally
forth, that he might have an occaſion to oblige his
Father, and be reveng'd for all the injuries had been
done him. <hi>Lucander,</hi> ſo ſoon as <hi>Pharnazes</hi> came
neare, gave notice to the reſt and aſſaulted him, crying,
Kill the Tyrant of <hi>Albania. Pharnazes</hi> called to <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimenes</hi>
to performe the promiſe, and protect his life.
He needed not much entreaty, for as ſoon as he ſaw
the ambuſh appeare, he came up to him, and ſo laid
about him on every ſide with the young Oake, that
hee diſperſed them, and if any oppoſ'd him,
he paid for his boldneſſe, by meaſuring his length
upon the ground. <hi>Lucander</hi> adventured, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence
of one blow to truſt to his Buckler, thinking to
get in with his ſword; but with ſuch fury did <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimenes</hi>
let fall upon his enemie, that he felled him to
the ground: The aſſiſtant Conſpirators afrighted at
his fall, left him and ran away: <hi>Pharnazes</hi> leading a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<hi>Lucander,</hi> ſent him to priſon, but concealed the
cauſe, fearing the ſouldiers might mutiny: Then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
alone with <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> entreated him to let him
know who he was to whom he owed life. <hi>Geſime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi>
yet unwilling to be known, anſwered, he was the
ſon of that mountain; but the reaſon which oblig'd
him to his defence with ſuch earneſtneſſe was the
intimate friendſhip he once had with one called <hi>Geſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menes,</hi>
who profeſt himſelfe his unfortunate Son.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Alas, ſaid <hi>Pharnazes,</hi> drowning his face in teares,
had he liv'd, this Traitor <hi>Lucander</hi> durſt not have
attempted ſo impious a Treaſon.</q> 
               <q>He not only lives
(anſwered <hi>Geſimenes</hi>) but ere many daies paſſe, I
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:114828:45"/>
ſhall be able to let you ſee him, as obedient ſtill, as
you had never us'd him unkindly.</q> 
               <q>Then believe if
me, (replyed <hi>Pharnazes</hi>) that very inſtant will I ſet
the Crowne of <hi>Albania</hi> upon his head; the Kingdome
will not be ſorrie for it: though they think he be
not heire while <hi>Lucander</hi> lives, yet there is more in
this then they know. You are his friend, and will
rejoyce at his happineſſe: that therefore you may
ſeeke him with greater diligence, bee attentive and
and heare what a low condition his Fate decreed
him, even before he was borne. </q>
               <hi>Geſimenes</hi> with won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
obſerved what his Father ſaid, and giving him
time to wipe away the teares of his affliction, heard
him proceede in this manner:</p>
            <q>
               <p>Know that in my youth I lov'd a Lady, with ſo
unreaſonable an affection, that I forgot both Heaven
and my ſelfe for her: This blind paſſion arriv'd at
ſuch a height, that the Queene and ſhe, beeing at once
both with child, and delivered of two Sons both in
one day, to make a tranſcendent expreſſion of my
love to her, I caus'd the children to be chang'd, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne
to any except heaven, and one who was my
Favorite. By this meanes <hi>Lucander,</hi> the ſonne of
my Miſtriſſe (ſuppoz'd the Queens) was eſteem'd
heire of the Kingdome, and I had a better pretence
for my affection. <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> who was indeed my
lawfull Son, had <hi>Clorinda</hi> (the Lady I moſt eſteem'd)
aſſign'd for his mother. The whole Kingdome won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
I ſhould hate <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> the ſon of her I ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;
and eſteeme <hi>Lucander</hi> whoſe mother I hated
I will not relate how cruelly I us'd <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:114828:45"/>
cannot but grieve you to heare it, if you love him:
my diſaffection proceeded ſo farre, as to baniſh him
<hi>Albania:</hi> If hee bee alive (as we had newes of his
death) he hath lived many yeares miſerably abroad
in ſtrange Countries. But the nature of man is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant,
the love I beare <hi>Clorinda</hi> vaniſh't, and my
undeceived underſtanding, perceiv'd its errour; then
began I ſo much to diſlike <hi>Lucander,</hi> that I intended
to have diſcovered his Birth; but I forbore, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
the Crowne would be without an heire, ſeeing
<hi>Geſimenes</hi> was wanting. But ſince <hi>Lucander</hi> proves ſo
ungratefull, as by treaſon to deprive me of life and
Scepter, &amp; you aſſure me <hi>Geſimenes</hi> lives; if you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
your promiſe in bringing him, you ſhall ſee
him King of <hi>Albania,</hi> that hee may have his owne,
and you in part be paid the debt is owing you for
my life: His happineſſe cannot but reflect on you
who are ſo much his friend.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Geſimenes</hi> was not able to containe his joy, but
falling downe at his Fathers feet diſcovered himſelfe,
ſaying he was <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> and that he was well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
with the miſeries Fortune had inflicted on him,
ſince he had been baniſht from his ſight; Now ſhee
had beſtow'd on him the happineſſe to reſcue his gray
haires. <hi>Pharnazes</hi> tranſported with ſuch joy to
ſee him alive, as the ſtrangeneſſe of the accident re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired,
embraced him moſt affectionately, and told
him that he ſhould goe along with him, for on the
morrow his Commanders ſhould kiſſe his hand, and
his preſence would animate the Souldiers, for they
all loved him extremely, and knowing his valour
would undertake the warre, with the greater reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:114828:46"/>
In this <hi>Geſimenes</hi> could not obey, excuſing
himſelfe with the acknowledgement of many favours
received from <hi>Perozes,</hi> of whoſe Forces he was Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,
yet that he had taken Armes againſt his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
was not to offend him (as he had ſhewne) but
to be a meanes of peace between both Kingdomes.
<hi>Geſimenes</hi> at parting enquired of him for his Wife
<hi>Polixena;</hi> he much troubled, deſired him not to ſpeak
of her; for it would afflict his heart to remember
the cruelty which her Father and <hi>Lucander</hi> had uſ'd
in her death.</p>
            <p>Let it not grieve you ſo much, ſaid <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> For
ſhe is living; and although it may ſeeme impoſſible, I
have long enjoy'd her company in this Deſart, for
Heaven doth favour innocence, and protect thoſe
Lives which Power and Fortune doe unjuſtly perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute.</p>
            <p>Hereupon <hi>Geſimenes</hi> departed joyfully: And <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nazes</hi>
was no leſſe glad for having found his ſon, and
with him his owne life, which had that night been
loſt, had it not been preſerved by <hi>Geſimenes.</hi> Then
communicating this ſtrange event to his Counſell, he
determined to treat with the King of <hi>Armenia,</hi> and
Prince <hi>Perezes</hi> concerning Peace, and the former
Marriage. The evening following a place of meeting
was appointed for the two Kings. The firſt thing they
did was the proclaming of <hi>Geſimenes</hi> King of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania,</hi>
and the ſame day <hi>Polixena</hi> was confirm'd his
Wife; the King and Queen of <hi>Armenia</hi> offering
themſelves to give her at the Temple. <hi>Perozes</hi> told
<hi>Pharnazes</hi> that the reaſon why he rejected the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
Marriage with the Princeſſe, was becauſe he
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:114828:46"/>
was already married to <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> who was Niece to
him, and Daughter to <hi>Geſimenes</hi> and <hi>Polixena.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon,
they both to informe him of the truth, replyed
that they had no further knowledge of her, then that
ſhe had been brought up ſome years in their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;
that the buſineſſe was now of ſuch conſequence,
that it would be unjuſt to deceive him; and though
they had reaſon to love <hi>Iſmenia</hi> as well as if ſhe were
their Daughter, yet in truth ſhe was but of poore and
meane Parentage.</p>
            <p>This ſtruck <hi>Perozes,</hi> as if he had heard the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
of his death, but it troubled him more, when
he underſtood <hi>Iſmenia</hi> could not be found; for ſeeing
a neceſſitie that her deceit muſt bee diſcovered, and
that ſhe muſt loſe <hi>Perozes,</hi> ſhame would not ſuffer
her to appeare; ſo ſhe retired into the woods, flying
from him ſhe loved, and intending to end her life in
that ſolitude. The Nuptialls were deferred till they
might have news of the loſt <hi>Iſmenia;</hi> for the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
couple were ſo diſcontented at her abſence that
their reſentment gave occaſion to many to ſuſpect ſhe
was indeed their Daughter, and that they denyed it
onely becauſe they were unwilling to give her to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rozes:</hi>
The truth was, they lov'd her ſo extremely,
that if <hi>Geſimenes</hi> had not known <hi>Iſmenias</hi> Parents
might have contradicted it, he would have owned her.
<hi>Perozes</hi> in great paſſion offered a great ſumme of
money to any that ſhould bring newes of her. <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimenes</hi>
calling to minde that ſhee had often told him
the place where ſhe was borne, inſtantly diſpatched
Meſſengers to informe themſelves with all diligence
of her Parents, and to ſee whether ſhee were not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:114828:47"/>
to them: After enquirie they found them, and
upon examination they confeſſed, <q>That <hi>Iſmenia</hi>
was not their Daughter, thought they had profeſſed
her ſuch almoſt ever ſince ſhee was borne; that a
Gentleman of <hi>Albania</hi> named <hi>Artaſpes</hi> one night
brought her to their houſe, to be brough up by them,
charging them upon forfeit of their lives, not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale
the ſecret to any; that three yeares agoe having
a deſire to match her with a Kinſman of theirs, on
the day intended for marriage ſhe ſtole away, ſince
which time they could never know whether ſhee
were alive or dead.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This encreaſed the admiration of all; ſeeing <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſpes</hi>
had brought her thither, they ſuppoſed ſhee
muſt bee his: He being at that time in <hi>Albania,</hi> they
ſent for him to declare what he knew concerning <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menia:</hi>
Being come hee deſired a little privacy with
<hi>Geſimenes,</hi> and thus ſpake unto him.</p>
            <q>
               <p>What I ſhall affirme of her that you call <hi>Iſmenia,</hi>
concernes none ſo much as your ſelfe to know; not
to keepe you in ſuſpence; Prince <hi>Lucander</hi> and my
ſelfe, walking late one night in the City, as wee
were returning to the Palace, a woman with her
Face vailed called to us, and addreſſing her
ſelfe to <hi>Lucander,</hi> hee ask'd her, (being well nigh
dead) if ſhe would goe along with him, or that hee
ſhould doe her any ſervice I would beſeech you (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
the Lady, delivering a Childe into his
armes) to carry this infant to <hi>Geſimenes,</hi> who will
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:114828:47"/>
eaſily know from whence it comes: and (believe
me) we may both be able to requite this favour: ſo
giving it to <hi>Lucander,</hi> (whom if ſhee had knowne
ſhe would ſooner have given it to a Lyon) ſhe went
away, deſiring us not to follow her, becauſe it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd
both her life and honour: We both ſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed,
deviſing who this Lady might be; for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
how intirely you did love <hi>Polixena,</hi> wee could
not perſwade our ſelves, that you ſhould have any
other affection, and <hi>Polixena</hi> living ſo carefully
watched, we as little ſuſpected it could be ſhe. In the
end we carried the child to my houſe, &amp; he gave me
order to deliver it to a Nurſe; the next day he under
ſtood <hi>Polixenas</hi> ſudden ſicknes, &amp; viewing the childs
countenance, was fully perſwaded it was hers and
yours. The rage of his jelouſie was incited by cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty,
and relying on his power he commanded me to
bring it that he might kill it, and performe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
he had made to ſend it you; when I underſtood
this unjuſt intent, I was as much perplexed as if the
Child had beene mine owne, ſo divine was the
beauty of it. I was (to ſay truth) afraid: if I obey'd
him not I loſt his favour, (for Princes for one diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure
forget the ſervices of our whole life) and
to obey him was contrarie to my piety: at laſt I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
to bring it to him, not to diſpleaſe him; but
as I was going to this bloudy Sacrifice heaven ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
to applaud my compaſſion, offering mee an
opportunity to ſave it: for underſtanding that a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
of mine had a child borne two dayes before,
newly dead, I tooke it; and wounding the innocent
breaſt, beſmeared it with the congealed blood, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:114828:48"/>
carried it to <hi>Lucander,</hi> who thinking it had beene
that which cauſed his jealouſie, commended my cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie,
and perfected his furious revenge on it, tearing
in pieces the poore Infant, and thus was it ſent to
you, the more to afflict you, that the grief of ſeeing
it might kill you: Hereupon enſued the misfortunes
that you know; when night was come I departed
privatly from <hi>Albania,</hi> and in a private place en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
for a Nurſe with whom I left the Child, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
her it was requiſite, that it ſhould not be known
that I brought it to her, and giving her two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
Crownes, I took my leave of her; ſince which
time, leſt <hi>Lucander</hi> might come to know it, I
never ſaw her but twice; This is all I know con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<hi>Iſmenia.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Geſimenes</hi> amazed to heare theſe things, doubted
whether the prodigie of his owne ſtorie and <hi>Iſmenia's</hi>
life were a Dream, or true: for according to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
of <hi>Artaſpes</hi> ſhe was his Daughter: And her
face had been ſufficient to prove it, if there had been
no other teſtimony. He flung his Armes about <hi>Artaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi>
neck, and promiſed him ſuch requitall, that hee
ſhould not repent his curteſie. He preſently related
all to <hi>Pharnazes, Perozes,</hi> and <hi>Polixena,</hi> and as great
was the joy of all, as their grief that <hi>Iſmenia</hi> was miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.
They went to ſeek her, <hi>Geſimenes</hi> as her Father,
<hi>Perozes</hi> as her Husband: <hi>Geſimenes</hi> went to the Hill
where he had formerly lived with her, &amp; at the ſide
of a Wood, he ſaw a man lying a long upon the gras:
comming neare, and asking what hee did there, hee
anſwered, he was a poore Souldier, that hearing a
Proclamation, promiſing ten thouſand Crownes to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:114828:48"/>
him that ſhould finde <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> out of a deſire to better
his Fortune he went to ſeeke her, and was not out of
hope to finde her, becauſe he had the ſame day ſeene
a woman on the top of the mountaine, cloathed with
skins of wild beaſts, whom hee ſuſpected to be <hi>Iſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia;</hi>
for as ſoone as ſhe heard that name, ſhe made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
ſo faſt, that it was impoſſible for him to overtake
her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geſimenes</hi> rewarded the Souldier for his informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and both aſcending the mountaine, they reſted
not untill they came to a Spring dreſt up with Ruſhes
and Flags, where under a Cypreſſe Tree they found
her aſleepe. <hi>Geſimenes</hi> related to his Daughter her
happie birth; at which ſhe rejoyced more for being
worthy of <hi>Perozes,</hi> then for being daughter to the
Prince of <hi>Albania.</hi> Returning to Court, ſhe accknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
thoſe for her Parents whom ſhe ever lov'd, as
if ſhe had knowne them to be ſo. And her Marriage
with <hi>Perozes</hi> was immediately Celebrated with much
Solemnity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
